<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Love's case: wherein is published, first, his several petitions to the Parliament. Secondly, a full narrative of the late dangerous design against the state, written with Mr. Loves own hand, and by him sent to the Parliament; wherein he setteth down his several meetings and secret actings with Major Alford, Maj. Adams, Col. Barton, Mr. Blackmore, Mr. Case, Mr. Cauton, Dr. Drake, Mr. Drake, Cap. Farr, Mr. Gibbons, Mr. Haviland, Major Huntington, Mr. Jenkins, Mr. Jaquel, Mr Jackson, Lieut. Col. Jackson, Cap. Massey, Mr. Nalton, Cap. Potter, Mr. Robinson, Mr. Sterks, Colonel Sowton, Colonel Vaughan, and others. Thirdly, Mr. Loves speech and prayer on the scaffold on Towerhil, August 22. 1651. Printed by an exact copy, taken in short-hand by John Hinde. Fourthly, animadversions on the said speech and prayer.</title>
            <author>Love, Christopher, 1618-1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 213 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3143</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E641_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E790_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202750</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862936</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862936</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115116</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88575)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115116)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 98:E641[10] or 120:E790[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Love's case: wherein is published, first, his several petitions to the Parliament. Secondly, a full narrative of the late dangerous design against the state, written with Mr. Loves own hand, and by him sent to the Parliament; wherein he setteth down his several meetings and secret actings with Major Alford, Maj. Adams, Col. Barton, Mr. Blackmore, Mr. Case, Mr. Cauton, Dr. Drake, Mr. Drake, Cap. Farr, Mr. Gibbons, Mr. Haviland, Major Huntington, Mr. Jenkins, Mr. Jaquel, Mr Jackson, Lieut. Col. Jackson, Cap. Massey, Mr. Nalton, Cap. Potter, Mr. Robinson, Mr. Sterks, Colonel Sowton, Colonel Vaughan, and others. Thirdly, Mr. Loves speech and prayer on the scaffold on Towerhil, August 22. 1651. Printed by an exact copy, taken in short-hand by John Hinde. Fourthly, animadversions on the said speech and prayer.</title>
                  <author>Love, Christopher, 1618-1651.</author>
                  <author>Hinde, John, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 67, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R.W. and Peter Cole at the printing-press in Cornhil, near the Royal Exchange.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "September. 9".</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: item at reel 120:E.790[1] lacks all after p. 66.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trials (Treason) --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115116:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>LOVE</hi>'s
CASE:
Wherein is Publiſhed,<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> His ſeveral Petitions
to the Parliament.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> A full Narrative
of the late Dangerous De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign
againſt the State,
written with Mr. <hi>Loves</hi>
own hand, and by him ſent
to the Parliament; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
he ſetteth down his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
Meetings and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
Actings with Major
<hi>Alford,</hi> Maj. <hi>Adams,</hi> Col.
<hi>Barton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Blackmore,</hi>
Mr. <hi>Caſe,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cauton,</hi> Dr.
<hi>Drake,</hi> Mr. <hi>Drake,</hi> Cap.
<hi>Farr,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gibbons,</hi> Mr.
<hi>Haviland,</hi> Major <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington,</hi>
Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> Mr.
<hi>Jaquel,</hi> Mr <hi>Jackſon,</hi> Lieut.
Col. <hi>Jackſon,</hi> Cap. <hi>Maſſey,</hi>
Mr. <hi>Nalton,</hi> Cap. <hi>Potter,</hi>
Mr. <hi>Robinſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sterks,</hi>
Colonel <hi>Sowton,</hi> Colonel
<hi>Vaughan,</hi> and others.</item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Mr. <hi>Loves</hi> Speech
and Prayer on the Scaffold
on Towerhil, <hi>Auguſt 22.
1651.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Printed by an Exact Copy,
taken in Short-hand by
<hi>JOHN HINDE.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Animadverſions
on the ſaid Speech and
Prayer.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <q>Whoſe hatred is covered by deceit, his wickedneſs ſhall be ſhewed
before the whole Congregation. Whoſo diggeth a pit, ſhall fall
therein: And he that rolleth a ſtone, it will return upon him,</q>
            <bibl>Prov. 26. 26, 27.</bibl>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. W.</hi> and <hi>Peter Cole</hi> at the Printing-Preſs
in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the Royal Exchange. 1651.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petitions">
            <div type="petition">
               <pb facs="tcp:115116:2"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115116:2"/>
               <head>To the Supream Authority, The Parliament
of the Commonwealth of England:</head>
               <head>The Humble Petition of Chriſtopher Love, a condemned Priſoner
in the Tower of London;</head>
               <opener>Moſt humbly ſheweth,</opener>
               <p>THat your Petitioner having received the Sentence of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Death by
the High Court of Juſtice, and is preparing himſelf in all humility
and ſerious ſubmiſſion to drink that bitter Cup, the terror where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
though much abated through the pardoning Mercies of God
in the blood of ſprinkling; yet your Petitioner being brought down to the
duſt of death, deſires to ſee the righteous Lord in this Sentence, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging
it to be juſt with the Moſt High to cut him off both in the middeſt of
his days, and in the midſt of his Miniſtry; He deſires to be deeply humbled
under the mighty hand of God, lying now before the Lord and you, putting
his mouth in the duſt, that there may be hope that the Lord will pardon his
manifold iniquities, and that your Honors will paſs by his Offences done con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to your Laws, which (as he formerly did, ſo ſtill doth confeſs) renders
him culpable, for which he is unfeignedly ſorry: Your Petitioner goeth not
about to plead Excuſe, but with an humble Submiſſion proſtrates himſelf at
your feet, acknowledging he hath offended againſt the Acts of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,
and thereby is fallen under your ſore diſpleaſure, of which he is very
deeply ſenſible and ſorrowful alſo.</p>
               <p rend="indent italic">Your Petitioner therefore (having no other refuge left him on earth to redeem
his Life from death, but the Favor of this Honorable Houſe) makes his
humble Addreſſes to you in the day of his deep Diſtreſs, that you would, as
the Elect of God, put on bowels of Compaſsion towards him, that his life may
be given him for a prey, that he may give his life for a Sacrifice for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of God and good of this Nation; and if the Lord ſhall pleaſe to ſtir up
your hearts to remit the Execution, and abſolve him from the Sentence of
Death, it will be to him as life from the dead, and he ſhall thankfully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
God as the Author, and you as the Inſtruments; and humbly hopes it
will be no matter of grief to you in the Great Day of your Accompt, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcue
his life from going down to the Pit, and he is perſwaded that hereby the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115116:3"/>
hearts of many that are godly, will be comforted and united, and many
Thankſgivings from them will redound to God in your behalf, and will lay
Obligations on your Petitioner the remainder of his days to lead a peaceable
and quiet life in all godlineſs and honeſty, and a Promiſe in his place and
calling to endeavor the Peace and Welfare of this Commonwealth.</p>
               <closer>And your Petitioner ſhall ever pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <signed>Chriſtopher Love.</signed> 
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Read</hi> 
                     <date>July 9. 1651.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>To the Supream Authority, The Parliament of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
of ENGLAND:</head>
               <head>The Humble Petition of Chriſtopher Love, a Condemned Priſoner in the
Tower of London;</head>
               <opener>Moſt humbly ſheweth,</opener>
               <p>THat your Petitioner doth with all Thankfulneſs acknowledge it a ſingular
Providence of God, and ſpecial Favor of the Parliament, that a door of
Hope is yet open, and opportunity once more offered to proſtrate himſelf at
your feet for a Grant of his Life, which if you vouchſafe, he ſhall accept as an
Act of great Grace and Mercy. It is no little grief of heart to your Petitioner,
that through unadviſedneſs and weakneſs he is fallen under your ſad and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy
Diſpleaſure, and hath offended againſt the Laws of this Commonwealth,
and now by the Sentence of the High Court of Juſtice (to which he ſubmits
with all Chriſtian meekneſs and humble acknowledgement of Gods hand
therein) is in inevitable and ſudden danger to loſe his Life, without your mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful
and gracious Interpoſition: And whereas there is a Surmiſe of a Plot
continued againſt the Peace and Welfare of this Commonwealth, he doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
in the preſence of God the Searcher of all hearts, that he knoweth no Plot
or Deſign againſt the preſent Government; nor is he privy in the leaſt to any
preparations for, or intendments towards any inteſtine Inſurrections or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign
Invaſions, or to any Correſpondencies now held with any in, or of the
Scotiſh Nation, or any other whatſoever: He is not ignorant how much Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants
will triumph at his death, nor is he without natural affections to his
dear Wife and Children, nor without real deſires of life to do God and his
Countrey ſervice, which are powerful Perſwaſions to him to do whatever he
can, without wounding his Conſcience.</p>
               <p rend="indent italic">Your dying Petitioner humbly prays, That as the Elect of God, you would put
on bowels of Compaſſion, and in imitation of your Heavenly Father, (whoſe
Mercy rejoyceth againſt Judgement) be pleaſed to abſolve him from the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115116:3"/>
Sentence of Death, which will be to him as life from the dead; and this new
Life received from your hands, will lay ſtrong Obligations on your Petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
to endeavor in his place and calling, the compoſing of Differences among
the Godly, and preſerving ſpiritual Peace and Love throughout the Churches
of the Saints, as well as the civil Peace and Welfare of the Commonwealth;
And he further promiſes neither to Plot, Contrive or Deſign any thing to
the hurt of this preſent Government; and if it ſhall be required, to put in
further Security for performance hereof; and if none of theſe things ſhould
move you to vouchſafe an Abſolute Pardon, yet let him implore thus much
from your hands, as his laſt, though very uncomfortable Requeſt, That you
would be pleaſed to change the Sentence of death, into Baniſhment into
ſome ſtrange Land, where he may ſit alone, lamenting his ſad and deplorable
Condition.</p>
               <closer>And your Petitioner ſhall pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <signed>Chriſtopher Love.</signed> 
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Read</hi> 
                     <date>July 11. 1651.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>To the Supream Authority, The Parliament of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
of ENGLAND:</head>
               <head>The humble Petition of Chriſtopher Love condemned to die, and the hour of
Execution drawing near;</head>
               <opener>Moſt humbly ſheweth,</opener>
               <p>THat whereas there are but very few hours between your Petitioner and
Death, he is humbly bold before he breathe out his ſoul to God, to breathe
out his Requeſt to the Parliament, by making his laſt Addreſs to you, humbly
acknowledging he hath incurred your high Diſpleaſure (of which he is deeply
ſenſible) and violated the Laws of this Commonwealth, for which he is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly
ſorrowful, and now alſo ſubmitteth to the Sentence of the High
Court, and promiſeth and offereth further Security neither to Plot, Contrive or
Deſign the Subverſion of this preſent Government, accounting it as a brand
of the higheſt Ingratitude to imploy his life againſt you, if he ſhould by an
Act of Grace and Favor receive a new life from you.</p>
               <p rend="indent italic">Wherefore your dying Petitioner, before he commend his ſoul to God on the Block,
he pours out his ſoul to you, at your Bar, That you would be pleaſed by your
gracious, merciful and ſeaſonable Interpoſition, to prevent this ſad ſtroke
now the hand is even lifted up, and he is as one giving up the ghoſt; and if
he have provoked you ſo far as to render him uncapable of an Abſolute Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,
yet he humbly beſeeches you to change the Sentence of death into perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115116:4"/>
Baniſhment; in ſo doing, your Mercy will triumph over Iuſtice, and
the greatneſs and nearneſs of his danger, he being as one free among the
dead, will exceedingly greaten the freeneſs of your Grace and Mercy.</p>
               <closer>And your Petitioner ſhall pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <signed>Chriſtopher Love.</signed> 
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Read</hi> 
                     <date>July 15. 1651.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>To the Supream Authority, The Parliament of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
of ENGLAND:</head>
               <head>The humble Petition of Mary the Wife of Chriſtopher Love;</head>
               <opener>SHEWETH,</opener>
               <p>THat your poor Petitioner hath great cauſe to ſay, Bleſſed be God, and
bleſſed be You, for your merciful Vote of the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Iuly</hi> (a Day never
to be forgotten) in adding a moneth to the Life of her dear Husband, which
hath opened a door of Hope to her in the midſt of the Valley of <hi>Achor,</hi> and
made her glad, though ſhe be a woman of a ſorrowful Spirit; yet your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed
Handmaid is overwhelmed with grief and anguiſh of Soul, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be comforted when ſhe remembers that doleful Day the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> ſo
near approaching, her heart doth almoſt die within her, and ſhe is as one giving
up the ghoſt, before ſhe is delivered of the fruit of her womb.</p>
               <p rend="indent italic">Wherefore your greatly diſtreſſed Handmaid doth again pour out her ſoul with
renewed and importunate Requeſts, Beſeeching your Honors to commiſerate
her deplorable Condition, by putting on bowels of Pity and Compaſſion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
her dear condemned Husband; that ſhe may not grapple with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable
pains of Travel, and the unſupportable thoughts of her Husband's
death in one day; O that the Life of your Handmaid and her Babe might
be a Ranſom for the Life of her condemned Husband! ſhe had rather chuſe
out of love to die for him, then for ſorrow of heart to die with him: Now
the good Lord incline your hearts to give him his life for a Prey, whereſoever
it ſhall pleaſe your Honors to cast him.</p>
               <closer>And your Petitioner ſhall ever pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <signed>Mary Love.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>To the Supream Authority, The Parliament of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
of ENGLAND:</head>
               <head>The humble Petition of Chriſtopher Love, a Condemned Priſoner in the
Tower of London;</head>
               <opener>SHEWETH,</opener>
               <p>THat your Petitioner doth humbly adore the wonderful Goodneſs of God,
and moſt thankfully acknowledge the great Mercy of the Parliament, for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115116:4"/>
ſo ſeaſonable and acceptable an Act of Grace to ſuch an offending Suppliant,
that when there was but a ſtep between him and death, the number of his days
being accompliſhed, and he almoſt cut off from the Land of the living, then you
mercifully interpoſed and gave him his Life for a moneth longer, which was to
him as a Reſurrection from the dead; The conſideration whereof melteth the
heart of your Petitioner, and makes him (after a more narrow ſearch into his
heart and ways) more deeply ſenſible then ever of his ſin againſt God, and more
ſorrowful for his high Crimes and Offences againſt the Parliament, in his late
and great Miſcarriages.</p>
               <p>He humbly acknowledgeth he hath ſo highly violated the Laws of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,
as that thereby he hath rendered himſelf guilty of the Sentence
of death, juſtly paſſed on him by the High Court of Juſtice; He doth alſo
herewith humbly offer to your Honors a free and full Narrative under his hand
of the whole Deſign (to the beſt of his remembrance) which he leaveth to
your grave Wiſdoms and favorable Interpretations, fully reſolving that he
will neither plot, contrive or deſign any thing prejudicial to the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;
but will in his place and calling oppoſe any Deſigns whatſoever
(whether in this or the neighbor Nation) that may tend to the ruine of this
Commonwealth.</p>
               <p rend="indent italic">Your dying Petitioner with all humble importunity proſtrates himſelf at your
feet, puts his mouth in the duſt, (O that there may be hope!) craving your
tender Mercy, begging his Life at your hands, promiſing never to imploy
that Life againſt you he ſhall receive from you, but doth hold it his Duty in
his place and calling, to lay out himſelf for the glory of God, the good of his
people, the Peace and Safety of this Commonwealth.</p>
               <closer>
And your Petitioner ſhall ever pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <signed>Chriſtopher Love.</signed> 
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Read</hi> 
                     <date>Auguſt 14. 1651.</date> 
                     <hi>Reod again</hi> 
                     <date>Auguſt 16. 1651.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="narrative">
            <head>A Brief and full
NARRATIVE
Humbly preſented, with my Petition to the Parliament,
By me CHRISTOPHER LOVE.</head>
            <p>COnſidering how a clear and full Narrative may ſatisfie the State (although
it may prejudice my ſelf) I am willing with an Ingenuous Freedom and
openneſs of heart to make known the whole matter, ſo far as I diſtinctly
know and well remember, humbly hoping that this large acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115116:5"/>
of mine (which is more then any in the world can prove againſt me)
ſhall not be taken as an Aggravation of my fault, but as a Demonſtration of
my Ingenuity. Before I mention the matters of Fact, I humbly crave leave to
ſignifie the time when, and maner how I came to be intangled in this unhappy
Buſineſs.</p>
            <p>As for the time, it was after the breaking off the Treaty between the King
and the Scots at <hi>Jerſey;</hi> for before that time (to the beſt of my remembrance)
I was not privy to, or acquainted with any meetings about the ſending of
Captain <hi>Titus</hi> (whoſe face I never ſaw) to <hi>Jerſey,</hi> or ſending Letters to him,
or receiving Letters from him whiles he was there; or about ſending any Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
to, or receiving Letters from the King, Queen, <hi>Jermyn, Piercy,</hi> or any
other perſon in Forraign parts during the Treaty at <hi>Jerſey:</hi> But after that
Treaty was ended, Mr. <hi>William Drake</hi> came to me, told me he had News to
impart; and to that end, he deſired to know (if he could get Friends toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther)
whether I was willing that they ſhould meet at my houſe (it being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently
ſcituate in the midſt of the City) that ſo he might communicate
what he heard of Affairs abroad. To ſatisfie my curioſity to hear News, I was
content to let him, with thoſe he ſhould bring to meet at my houſe: Thus for
the time when and maner how I came to be preſent at any meetings about In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence.</p>
            <p>I now come humbly and truly to relate the matter of Fact, which is as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth;
It appeared to me by the Teſtimony of the Witneſſes, that there
were frequent meetings by Mr. <hi>Drake, Alford, Titus, Adams,</hi> and others,
ſoon after the death of the late King; and Applications made to the King
of Scots, the Queen his Mother, to <hi>Jermyn</hi> and <hi>Piercy,</hi> both before and
during the Treaty at <hi>Jerſey,</hi> of which I know nothing, nor was I preſent: But
the firſt meeting I was at was at my houſe, and was (as I remember) at the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of a Letter which came from Captain <hi>Titus</hi> after the Treaty was ended at
<hi>Jerſey;</hi> the Contents of that Letter was (if I miſtake not) to this effect: That
the Treaty at <hi>Jerſey</hi> was broken off through the violent and evil Counſels of
deſperate Malignants; and that he had ſomething of concernment to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate,
which he durſt not do in perſon, being not ſafe for him to come
over into <hi>England,</hi> nor could he well do it by writing, he judging it not fit nor
ſafe to ſend by the common Poſt, fearing a miſcarriage; wherefore he deſired
ſome body to be ſent over to him to <hi>Calice,</hi> to whom he might give an accompt
of all Proceedings. Upon the reading of this Letter, Mr. <hi>Drake</hi> moved that
ſome perſon ſhould be deſired to go to <hi>Calice;</hi> for ſaid he, We ſhall hear the
whole Relation of the buſineſs at <hi>Jerſey:</hi> Whereupon Major <hi>Adams</hi> or Cap.
<hi>Farr</hi> were moved by Mr. <hi>Drake</hi> to go. There was mention of Major <hi>Alford</hi>
to go, though he was not preſent that I know of; nor was he ever within my
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115116:5"/>
houſe, as I remember, until after he returned from <hi>Calice:</hi> So that there was
none that I know of was gone. Mr. <hi>Drake</hi> told me, Major <hi>Alford</hi> was the
fitteſt man to go over to <hi>Calice,</hi> having buſineſs of his own to go into <hi>France,</hi>
to look after his Prodigal ſon: So that it was (ſaid he) a plauſible pretence to
conceal his going over to meet with <hi>Titus.</hi> There were preſent at this firſt
meeting, Mr. <hi>Drake,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> Major <hi>Adams,</hi> Dr. <hi>Drake,</hi> Cap. <hi>Farr,</hi> Cap.
<hi>Potter,</hi> and my ſelf, with ſome others; but who more, I cannot remember.</p>
            <p>About two or three days after Major <hi>Alfords</hi> return from <hi>Calice,</hi> Mr.
<hi>Drake</hi> told me he was come to <hi>London,</hi> and told me he would go to ſeveral
Miniſters and Citizens, to deſire them to meet at my houſe, that ſo we might
hear what news Major <hi>Alford</hi> brought with him from <hi>Calice,</hi> accordingly the
next day in the Evening they met at my houſe, Mr. <hi>Drake</hi> brought Major
<hi>Alford</hi> with him; Major <hi>Alford</hi> at that meeting gave an accompt of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
with <hi>Titus,</hi> and of his receiving a Copy of the Kings Letter from him,
as alſo a Narrative of the Proceedings at the Treaty of <hi>Jerſey:</hi> But he ſaid (if
I miſtake not) that he brought not over the Letters himſelf, but delivered them
to a Paſſenger that came over in the Ship to carry them, leſt that himſelf
ſhould be ſearched; but after he came into <hi>England,</hi> he received the Letter and
Narrative from the Paſſenger (but who he was I know not) and ſo brought
them to <hi>London,</hi> Whether the Copy of the Kings Letter was read at my
houſe in my hearing, I remember not; yet I deny not, but it was read there:
I am ſure I heard that the Contents of it, were to this effect, That he
took in good part the Affections and Loyalty of thoſe who formerly had
made Applications by way of Petition to him (of which Petition I know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing)
And if ever God reſtored him or put him in a Condition, he ſhould
remember them. The Narrative which <hi>Alford</hi> brought from <hi>Titus,</hi> was read
in my houſe in my hearing, which was to this effect, He made a large Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> commending his Prudent Carriage and good Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
to an Agreement with the <hi>Scots,</hi> but that his bad Councel about him
hindered it: Alſo he made a Rehearſal of his Sufferings from the Cavaliers at
<hi>Jerſey,</hi> how he was impriſoned in a cloſe Room: Many things elſe was in the
Narrative which I have forgotten. There were preſent at this meeting, Major
<hi>Alford,</hi> Mr. <hi>Drake,</hi> Mr. <hi>Caſe,</hi> Major <hi>Adams,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jaquel,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jackson,</hi> Mr.
<hi>Jenkins,</hi> Doctor <hi>Drake,</hi> Cap. <hi>Potter,</hi> M. <hi>Sterks,</hi> Cap. <hi>Farr,</hi> and my ſelf, with
ſome others; but who more, I do not remember.</p>
            <p>A little before or about the Treaty, between the King and the <hi>Scots</hi> at
<hi>Breda,</hi> there was a meeting at my houſe, Mr. <hi>Drake</hi> propoſed, That we ſhould
think of ſome way to promote the Agreement between the King and the
<hi>Scots;</hi> where by the way, I deſire humbly to give notice, That this was the
firſt and onely meeting of this nature, and for this end, as my houſe, that I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115116:6"/>
know of. At this meeting, Mr. <hi>Drake</hi> took out ſome Papers out of his Pocket
written in Characters, which he read in my Study; What he read, went un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the name of a Commiſſion and Inſtructions (as he termed it) to be ſent to
the Lord <hi>Willoughby;</hi> Alderman <hi>Bunce, Maſſey, Graves</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point
them to adviſe with, and uſe their Intereſt in Perſons of Honor about the
King, to provoke him to agree with the <hi>Scots,</hi> and to take the Covenant; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
to adviſe with the <hi>Scots</hi> Commiſsioners, and perſwade them, That in their
Agreemnt with their King, they would have ſpecial reſpect to the Intereſt of
Religion, and terms of the Covenant; the Commiſſion ran in this form, as if
it were in the names of all the Presbyterial party in <hi>England:</hi> After I heard it
read, I expreſſed my ſelf againſt it, alledging ſeveral Reaſons, chiefly, That it
was an Act of high Preſumption for private perſons to ſend Commiſſion with
Inſtructions, and an act of notorious falſhood, to ſay, This was in the name
of the Presbyterial party of <hi>England;</hi> when none but a few perſons then
preſent knew thereof that I know of: Many in the Company did expreſs a
diſlike thereof, as well as my ſelf; I mention not this my diſcent as an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy
to excuſe my ſelf, I know a condemned man ſhould not plead an excuſe,
but meerly as a Relation of ſuch Circumſtances which will make my Narrative
more clear and full: I ſhall anon mention particulars rather to aggravate, then
extenuate my fault. But to return to the buſineſs of this meeting, Mr. <hi>Draks</hi>
did alſo read a Letter in this meeting, but to whom it was, I know not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
know I the Contents of it; I was at leaſt a dozen times called out of the
Room, whiles the Company were there met; ſo that I am not able to give ſo
full and particular an accompt of the Contents of the Letter, and of the
Commiſſion and Inſtructions: What Mr. <hi>Drake</hi> did about the Commiſſion
and Inſtructions after he was gone from my houſe, I know not; what he ſent
away, I know not; nor did I know by whom it was ſent away, until Major
<hi>Alford</hi> declared before the High Court, That he received the Papers from Mr.
<hi>Drake,</hi> carried them to <hi>Graveſend,</hi> and delivered them to one <hi>Maſon</hi> (whoſe
face I never ſaw) and he carried them to <hi>Holland.</hi> There were preſent at this
meeting, Major <hi>Huntingdon</hi> (who was never at my houſe before nor ſince,
whoſe face I never ſaw before, nor ſince, but at my Tryal) There were preſent
alſo Mr. <hi>Drake,</hi> Dr. <hi>Drake,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jackson,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cauton,</hi> Major
<hi>Alford,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gibbons,</hi> Major <hi>Adams,</hi> Cap. <hi>Farr,</hi> and my ſelf, with ſome others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
whom I cannot remember.</p>
            <p>I was preſent ſometimes at private Faſts, particularly at Major <hi>Adams</hi>
and Colonel <hi>Bartons;</hi> in both places I ſaw on the Table, a Paper written, by
whom know not; where among other ends of thoſe Faſts, this one End was
ſpecified, To deſire a Bleſſing upon the Treaty between the King and the <hi>Scots.</hi>
At Major <hi>Adams</hi> houſe Mr. <hi>Caſe</hi> Preached and I prayed, but who elſe exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115116:6"/>
I remember not. I confeſs I did in that Faſt pray, That God would
reſcue the King from Wicked and Malignant Councels, That God would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem
him from the Iniquity of his Fathers houſe, That there might be a firm
Agreement between him and his Subjects of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſuch as might conſiſt
with the Intereſt of Religion, and Terms of the Covenant. Preſent at this
meeting, Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> Mr. <hi>Caſe,</hi> Doctor <hi>Drake,</hi> Mr. <hi>Robinſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cauton,</hi>
Mr. <hi>Sterks,</hi> Mr. <hi>Drake,</hi> Major <hi>Adams,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jaquel,</hi> my ſelf and many others;
but I cannot call one more to minde.</p>
            <p>There was a Faſt alſo at Col. <hi>Bartons,</hi> where Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> and my ſelf
Preached, Mr. <hi>Caſe,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cauton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Robinſon</hi> prayed, ſundry other perſons
were preſent; but I remember none but Col. <hi>Barton,</hi> Dr. <hi>Drake,</hi> Lieut. Col.
<hi>Jackson,</hi> Mr. <hi>Drake</hi> and Major <hi>Adams.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About a year ſince Captain <hi>Potter</hi> ſpake to me to deſire ſome money for
a good uſe, for a poor Scotchman who was to leave this Nation, his name
was <hi>Sterks,</hi> but he was no Agent for any in <hi>Scotland</hi> that I know of: I gave
Captain <hi>Potter</hi> Ten ſhillings to give to him.</p>
            <p>In the moneth of <hi>July, 1650.</hi> or thereabouts, there was a rough-draft of
a Letter read in my houſe, intended to be ſent to the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> by
whom it was written, I know not, by whom it was read I remember not, I
heard but a part of it read, The ſubſtance of that part of the Letter which I
heard, was to ſignifie the great ſufferings that many of the Brethren here were
under, what ſnares and dangers we were daily in; yet to aſſure them of our
ſtedfaſtneſs to the Covenant, to which end we deſired the help of their prayers,
promiſing them ours: I declared my ſelf againſt the ſending away of this
Letter, yet it was (as I heard) written afterwards by Mr. <hi>William Drake,</hi>
and that with Sack in a Table Book, or Paper Book, and ſent away by one
Col. <hi>Bampfield</hi> (whoſe face I never ſaw) and without my knowledge or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
carried by him into <hi>Scotland:</hi> There were preſent at this meeting, Cap.
<hi>Potter,</hi> Doctor <hi>Drake,</hi> Major <hi>Adams,</hi> Major <hi>Alford</hi> Mr. <hi>Sterks,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jeaquel,</hi>
Mr. <hi>Gibbons,</hi> Cap. <hi>Farr,</hi> and my ſelf, with ſome others whom I remember not.</p>
            <p>After <hi>Dunbar</hi> fight, there was a rough-draft of a Letter read in my houſe,
it was ſpoken to be directed to the Commiſſioners of the General Aſſembly
of the Church of <hi>Scotland;</hi> The rough-draft was read by Doctor <hi>Drake,</hi> but
that it was written by him, I cannot poſitively ſay: I ſuppoſe he drew up that
Letter and Copy which was ſent away, but cannot affirm it. I confeſs I did
offer ſome general Heads to be inſerted in the Letter before it was drawn up,
which were to this effect: Firſt, To intimate that their Brethren here did
ſenſibly lay to heart their ſad loſs, That ſo many of them ſhould fall by the
hands of their Brethren. Secondly, To deſire them to ſearch into the cauſe
of the Lords ſevere diſpleaſure againſt them. Thirdly, To underſtand the true
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115116:7"/>
ſtate of their Affairs ſo far as was fit for them to impart; and for us to know,
Whether they did ſtill maintain Religious and Covenant-Intereſt. There were
preſent at this meeting, Mr. <hi>Caſe,</hi> Major <hi>Adams,</hi> Doctor <hi>Drake,</hi> Captain
<hi>Maſſey,</hi> Lieut. Col. <hi>Jackson,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gibbons,</hi> Cap. <hi>Potter,</hi> and my ſelf, with
ſome others whom I remember not.</p>
            <p>Soon after this, there was a Letter read in my houſe by Cap. <hi>Maſſey,</hi> as
was ſaid to be from Major General <hi>Maſſey,</hi> which was the firſt Letter that I
remember was read in my houſe, which came from <hi>Scotland;</hi> This was neer
three moneths after <hi>Dunbar</hi> fight: Together with this Letter from <hi>Maſſey,</hi>
there were Letters read from Alderman <hi>Bunce</hi> and Mr. <hi>Drake</hi> at the ſame
time (if I miſtake not) The ſubſtance of Alderman <hi>Bunces</hi> and Mr. <hi>Drakes</hi>
Letters, I have wholly forgotten; but the Contents of <hi>Maſſeys</hi> Letter was to
this Effect, He mentioned the Poverty of his Condition, to what Neceſſities
both <hi>Titus</hi> and himſelf were reduced, having no Command at all in the Scotiſh
Army: He alſo in his Letter related the number of the <hi>Scots,</hi> who were both
ſlain and taken priſoners; and wrote for Money and Arms to be ſent him, by
the way of <hi>Holland:</hi> All the company was againſt ſending money on a Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary
Accompt to provide Arms; all did diſavow that: But there was a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
made (by whom I know not) to ſend them money for a ſupply of
their perſonal Neceſſities: The ſum propounded was, either Three hundred
pounds, or elſe Four hundred pounds. I confeſs, I did ſecond this Propoſal, and
did move for the Contribution of money for them, but named no ſum, and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
diſclaimed the buſineſs of Arms: I moved it chiefly for <hi>Maſſey</hi> (for I
knew not <hi>Titus)</hi> becauſe <hi>Maſſey</hi> had formerly done eminent Services for the
good of this Nation; and I moved it meerly for a ſupply of his perſonal Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities,
without any reference to the War: I confeſs, I did ſubſcribe Ten
pounds for that purpoſe, and did give it accordingly, laying it down on the
Table in my Parlor, wrapt up in a Paper with <hi>C. L.</hi> written on it. There
were many preſent in the Room, but none ſaw me lay it down (that I know
of) nor did I ſee any take it up, yet I believe Cap. <hi>Maſſey</hi> received it. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs,
I did not onely ſubſcribe the ſum that I my ſelf did give, but I did write
down alſo ſome few of the ſums, which others ſaid they would give: Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly
I writ down Ten pounds which Lieut. Col. <hi>Jackson</hi> promiſed to give, Ten
pounds which Maj. <hi>Adams</hi> promiſed to give, and Five pounds which Cap. <hi>Farr</hi>
promiſed to give, and Five pounds which Mr. <hi>Jaquel</hi> told me of before, if
there were need he would give: But I received not the money from any of
thoſe forementioned, but onely from Mr. <hi>Jaquel</hi> I received Five pounds for
the uſe of <hi>Maſſey</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> and the next meeting laid it on my Table, wrapt
in a Paper, with Mr. <hi>Jaquel</hi> written on it. I might poſſibly receive Five or ten
pounds from ſome of the company, who met at my houſe, for the uſe of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115116:7"/>
               <hi>Maſſey,</hi> but cannot now remember from whom. There were ſeveral ſums of
money left on my Table, but I ſaw them not laid down, nor did I ſee any take
it up; yet I ſuppoſe Cap. <hi>Maſſey</hi> did receive it, and return it.</p>
            <p>I do confeſs, I writ an anſwer to <hi>Maſſey</hi>'s Letter, which none in the
World could accuſe me of; it was the firſt and onely Letter that ever I writ
into <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſince the Wars began: I writ it in long hand, for I never
uſed Cypher or Character in all my life. And though before the High Court
I did ſay (and that truly) I never wrote Letter to any perſon of the Scotiſh
Nation, ſince the Wars began, yet I durſt not ſay, I never writ to any perſon
in the Scotiſh Nation, becauſe I did write this one (and but this one) Letter
to <hi>Maſſey:</hi> The ſubſtance of the Letter was to this effect, To let him know,
his Friends here could not forget the eminent Services he had formerly done;
That we were ſorry to hear of the Neceſſity of his Condition; That ſome
Friends here had reſolved, as an Expreſſion of their Reſpects towards him and
Cap. <hi>Titus,</hi> to ſend them Four hundred pounds (although I believe that ſum was
never raiſed) for a ſupply of their perſonal Neceſſities: But as for Arms, I
wrote expreſly, We could not, we would not provide any; it was neither
ſafe, nor fit for us to ingage in a buſineſs of that nature: Wherefore I prayed
him to forbear any ſuch motions to us. There were preſent at this meeting
theſe perſons following, Major <hi>Alford,</hi> Lieut. Col. <hi>Jackson,</hi> Mr. <hi>Caſe,</hi> Cap.
<hi>Maſſey,</hi> Major <hi>Adams,</hi> Dr. <hi>Drake,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gibbons,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cauton,</hi> Cap. <hi>Farr,</hi> and
my ſelf, with ſome others; but who more, I cannot well remember.</p>
            <p>There is one thing I have yet to declare concerning a learned and godly
Brother, Dr. <hi>Drake,</hi> which I hope will not turn to his prejudice; He did
twice or thrice bring Letters to my houſe, and read them when we met: I
believe they were from his Brother <hi>M. William Drake</hi> who is in <hi>Holland,</hi> the
matter of them was, An expreſſion of Brotherly affection, a remembring to
Friends, and a relation of what News he heard either in <hi>Scotland</hi> or <hi>Holland,</hi>
and an exciting ſometimes to do ſomething to raiſe money for the Scots, which
motion Dr. <hi>Drake</hi> did reject, and (as he told me) writ a Denial. Dr. <hi>Drake</hi>
did alſo ſhew me the Tranſcript of a Letter (which he ſaid) was from the King;
it was written in his Brothers Letter; the ſubſtance of it was to this effect,
That he was glad he was joyned in the ſame Covenant with ſuch honeſt men,
as he had cauſe to judge them to be; but to whom the Letter was written I
know not, nor can I remember one paſſage more in it.</p>
            <p>About <hi>February</hi> laſt paſt, Capt. <hi>Potter</hi> (and <hi>M. Jaquel</hi> with him) brought
Letters to my houſe, which was the laſt Meeting (to the beſt of my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance)
at my houſe about a buſineſs of ſuch a nature, when Capt. <hi>Potter</hi> came
in, he ſaid, He had News to ſhew me, and took out of his pocket ſeveral Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
I think they were moſt, if not all opened, before he brought them to my
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115116:8"/>
houſe: One Letter was from <hi>M. Bayly</hi> a Miniſter in <hi>Scotland,</hi> another from
Col. <hi>Bampfield,</hi> a third ſubſcribed by four Lords of <hi>Scotland, viz. Argyle, Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,
Lothian</hi> and <hi>Belcarris;</hi> there was a Letter or two more, but from whom
or to whom, I know not; I cannot remember the Contents of each Letter
on the bare hearing Capt. <hi>Potter</hi> reading of them, onely in one or more of
them, there was a Narration of the Affairs of <hi>Scotland,</hi> how they ſtood ſince
<hi>Dunbar</hi> Fight; what Diviſions and Parties there were in <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſome for the
King, others for the Kirk, and ſome for neither. There was a motion alſo for
10000 l. to be raiſed for the Affairs of <hi>Scotland,</hi> but all preſent diſliked the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and did utterly refuſe to act any thing in that buſineſs, and reſolved to
give a Negative Anſwer: I was deſired to write an Anſwer to Col. <hi>Bampfield,</hi>
which I did, but who writ anſwer to the other Letters I do not know certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
onely this I know, Dr. <hi>Drake</hi> was deſired to return an Anſwer to <hi>M. Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi>
which I believe he did: It was agreed on by us who were preſent, That
though we did diſlike the motion for raiſing ſo great a ſum for the Scotiſh Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs,
yet we would ſend a Gratuity to the meſſenger; we judged it conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
to give Col. <hi>Bampfield</hi> and his man 40 l. In theſe Letters ſent by Col. <hi>Bamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi>
were an Anſwer to that Letter which <hi>M. Drake</hi> writ with Sack in a
Table-book or Paper-book, which was ſent in <hi>Iuly 1650.</hi> but the Anſwer not
returned till the <hi>February</hi> following. I confeſs I writ an Anſwer to Col. <hi>Bamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi>'s
Letter, but to none of the reſt; I wrote (though I knew not the man)
on purpoſe to ſtop further Solicitations to us for money; the Contents of the
Letter was to this effect, To give him notice of the Receipt of his Letter with
the Letters incloſed; I did write peremptorily, we could not, we would not
raiſe any moneys, it was neither fit nor ſafe for us to do ſo, I deſired him to
deſiſt any ſuch motions for the future, telling him we ſhould not ſatisfie his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation
and the Scots; I writ plainly to him, that we had no occaſion to
uſe or employ him in any buſineſs for us: I gave him notice alſo of 30 l. ſent
him, and 10 l. given his man, for their care and pains. This was the ſum of that
Letter I writ to Col. <hi>Bampfield</hi> who was then in <hi>Holland.</hi> Beſides one Letter
to <hi>Maſſey</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and this to <hi>Bampfield</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> I never writ any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
about buſineſs of this nature; moreover I gave 5 l. towards the 40 l. and
delivered it to <hi>M. Jaquel,</hi> but whether he returned it or who elſe I do not
certainly know, nor who elſe made up the ſum of 40 l. I know not; onely
this I know, it was agreed upon that among our ſelves we ſhould raiſe that
ſum, and ſo have no more to do with <hi>Bampfield;</hi> there were preſent when
the Letters were read which were ſent by <hi>Bampfield,</hi> Dr. <hi>Drake,</hi> Captain <hi>Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
Mr. <hi>Jaquel,</hi> and my ſelf: This was the laſt meeting, as I remember, which
was at my houſe about theſe Tranſactions, I was unwilling to continue it any
longer.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115116:8"/>
There is one thing more I make bold to mention, That there are other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
beſides thoſe I have named, who did now and then come to theſe Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
at my Houſe; as Mr. <hi>Robinſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Nalton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Haviland,</hi> Mr. <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi>
Col: <hi>Vaughan,</hi> Col: <hi>Sowton;</hi> theſe were alſo preſent at one time or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other,
but at what particular Meeting I cannot poſitively ſay.</p>
            <p>Thus I have clearly laid open the whole matter of Fact ſo far as I well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
and diſtinctly know of Paſſages about theſe Meetings and Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
at my Houſe; yea, I have expreſſed more then all the Witneſſes have
proved, or then all the men in the world could prove againſt me; and now I
humbly hope, the Parliament will be as free in pardoning, as I am in confeſſing,
that as by what I have done, I am an object of your juſt diſpleaſure; ſo by
what I have confeſſed, I may become an object of your free grace and favor.</p>
            <p>I fully reſolving never to ingage again in a buſineſs of the like nature, if
through your clemency you paſs by theſe ſundry and great Offences upon my
free Confeſſion, and full reſolution to leave them, you will reſemble God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
who hath ſaid, <hi>He that confeſſeth and forſakes his ſins ſhall finde mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus laid open my heart in this matter, in an ingenuous acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement,
I humbly crave leave to expreſs my ſelf in a few Particulars for
further ſatisfaction to the Parliament.</p>
            <p>1. Although I was preſent at ſeveral meetings in my Houſe to hear Letters
read, yet I uſed not to be at meetings elſewhere about buſineſſes of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;
it ſeems there were meetings in other places many Moneths before I
knew any thing.</p>
            <p>2. There are no perſons who uſed theſe meetings, ſo far as I remember (and
as I am informed) but they are already diſcovered and made known.</p>
            <p>3. There is no Intelligence or Correſpondencies now held that I know of,
with any in, or of the Scotiſh Nation, or any imployed by them.</p>
            <p>4. I am not privy to, or acquainted with any Plots or Deſigns now carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
on, for raiſing inteſtine Inſurrections at home, or joyning with Forreign
Invaſions from abroad.</p>
            <p>5. There was never any money raiſed that I know of, for any of the Scotiſh
Nation to carry on their War; yea, when Letters were read wherein there
were motions to that purpoſe, I utterly refuſed to do any thing therein.</p>
            <p>6. I do retain as vehement a Deteſtation of Malignancy, whether in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
or in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as ever I did, and ſhall in my Place and Calling oppoſe
ſuch a Deſign and intereſt with as much zeal and faithfulneſs as ever.</p>
            <p>7. Laſtly, I do faithfully promiſe never to ingage in a buſineſs of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
as this, wherein I have been inſnared; nor ſhall I Plot, Contrive or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign
the ſubverſion of this preſent Government, but ſhall under the ſame, lead
a peaceable and quiet life in all godlineſs and honeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115116:9"/>
I have no more to ſay, but to make this humble and laſt requeſt, That
this my large Confeſſion may not be taken as an Aggravation of my fault, but
as a Demonſtration of my Ingenuity. I acknowledge by your Juſtice, you
might in one day leave a Flock without a Shepherd, a Wife without a Husband,
Children without a Father, and a Body without a Soul: But my Hope and
Prayer is, That your Mercy will triumph over Juſtice, That I ſhall hear that
joyful ſound, That my life ſhall ſee the Light, That I ſhall be reſcued from
going down to the Grave: To which, if God ſhall incline your hearts, I ſhall
devote the remainder of my days, to the glory of God, and good of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
The peace and ſafety of this Commonwealth, againſt all the Malignant
Enemies, and Oppoſers thereof.</p>
            <p>I have but one Requeſt more to make to this Honorable Houſe, That if
ſome Paſſages about theſe Meetings and Tranſactions have paſſed my Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
or ſlipt my Memory (as happily through tract of time ſome things have)
That you would not impute it to my Wilfulneſs, but to my Forgetfulneſs of
things done ſo long ago.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From the Tower of <hi>London,</hi>
                  <date>July 22. 1651.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>I Atteſt the truth of this Narrative
under my Hand.
Chriſtopher Love.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <head>Mr. Love's Speech made on the Scaffold on
Tower-Hill, Auguſt 22. 1651.</head>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Love</hi> being brought upon the Scaffold by the Sheriffs, Mr. Sheriff
<hi>Titchburn</hi> ſhewed him the Warrant directed to the Sheriffs of <hi>London</hi>
for his Execution, telling him that he took no pleaſure in this Work, but it
was a Duty laid upon him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which Mr.</hi> Love <hi>replyed,</hi> I believe it, Sir.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sheriff <hi>Titchburn.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p> I have done my duty for you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. Love.</speaker>
               <p> 
                  <hi>The Lord bleſs you.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieutenant of the Tower.</speaker>
               <p> The Lord ſtrengthen you in this hour of your
Temptation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. Love.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi> Sir, I am. I bleſs God my heart is in heaven. I am well.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sheriff <hi>Titchburn.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p> I deſire you to conſider we have the other to execute
afterwards, and ſix a clock is our Hour; but we ſhall give you as much time
as we can.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:115116:9"/>
               <speaker>Mr. Love.</speaker>
               <p> 
                  <hi>I ſhall be the briefer.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <p>Then putting off his Hat two ſeveral
times to the people, he ſpake as followeth;</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECTION I.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BEloved Chriſtians,</hi> I am made this day a Spectacle unto God, Angels
and Men, and among men I am made a Grief to the Godly, a Laughing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtock
to the wicked, and a Gazing-ſtock to all, yet bleſſed be my God not
a Terror to my ſelf, although there be but a little between me and Death, yet
this bears up my heart, there is but a little between me and Heaven. It com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted
Doctor <hi>Tailor</hi> the Martyr when he was going to Execution, that there
were but two Styles between him and his Fathers houſe; there is a leſſer way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
me and my Fathers houſe; but two ſteps between me and Glory, it is but
lying down upon the Block, and I ſhall aſcend upon a Throne: I am this day ſayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
towards the Ocean of Eternity, through a rough Paſſage, to my Haven of
Reſt; through a Red-ſea to the Promiſed Land. Me thinks I hear God ſay to
me as he did to <hi>Moſes, Go up to Mount</hi> Nebo <hi>and die there,</hi> ſo go thou up to
<hi>Tower-hill</hi> and die there. <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſaid of himſelf that he was old, and yet he knew
not the day of his death, but I cannot ſay thus: I am yong, and yet I know the
day of my death, and I know the kinde of my death alſo, and the place of my death
alſo; it is ſuch a kinde of death as two famous Preachers of the Goſpel were put
to before me, <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle, they were both beheaded;
ye have mention of the one in Scripture Story, and of the other in Eccleſiaſtical
Hiſtory: And I read in the <hi>20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </hi> of the <hi>Revelation</hi> and the <hi>4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, The Saints were
beheaded for the Word of God, and for the Teſtimony of Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECTION II.</head>
               <p>But herein is the diſadvantage which I am in in the thoughts of many, who
judge that I ſuffer not for the Word, or for Conſcience, but for medling with
State matters. To this I ſhall briefly ſay, That it is an old guiſe of the Devil,
to impute the cauſe of Gods Peoples Sufferings, to be Contrivements againſt the
State, when in truth it is their Religion and Conſcience they are perſecuted for.
The Rulers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they would put <hi>Jeremiah</hi> to death upon a Civil account,
though indeed it was onely the truth of his Propheſie made the Rulers angry with
him; yet upon a Civil account they did pretend he muſt dye, becauſe he fell away
to the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> and would have brought in Forreign Forces to Invade them:
The ſame thing is laid to my charge, of which I am as innocent as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> was.
I finde other inſtances in the Scripture, wherein men the cauſe of their Sufferings
were ſtill imputed to medling with State-matters; <hi>Paul,</hi> though he did but
Preach Jeſus Chriſt, yet he muſt dye, if the People might have their will, under
the pretence that he was a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver of Sedition. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon a civil account my life is
pretended to be taken away, whereas indeed it is becauſe I purſue my Covenant,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115116:10"/>
and will not proſtitute my Principles and Conſcience to the Ambition and Luſts
of men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>Beloved, I am this day to make a double exchange, I am changing a Pulpit
for a Scaffold, and a Scaffold for a Throne; and I might adde a third, I am
changing this numerous multitude, the preſence of this numerous multitude upon
Tower-Hill, for the innumerable company of Angels in the holy Hill of <hi>Zion;</hi>
and I am changing a guard of Soldiers for a guard of Angels, which will receive
me, and carry me into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſom. This Scaffold it is the beſt Pulpit I
ever preached in; for in the Church-Pulpit, God through his Grace, made me an
Inſtrument to bring others to Heaven, but in this Pulpit he will bring me to
Heaven. Theſe are the laſt words that I ſhall ſpeak in this world, and it may be
this laſt Speech upon a Scaffold may bring God more glory, then many Sermons in
a Pulpit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p>Before I lay down my Neck upon the Block, I ſhall lay open my Caſe unto the
people that hear me this day, and in doing it I ſhall avoid all rancer, all bitterneſs
of Spirit, animoſity and Revenge, God is my record whom I ſerve in the ſpirit, I
ſpeak the truth, and lye not; I do not bring a revengeful heart unto the Scaffold
this day; before I came here, upon my bended knees I have begged Mercy for them
that denyed mercy to me, and I have prayed God to forgive them who would not
forgive me; I have forgiven from my heart the worſt Enemy I have in all the
world, and this is the worſt that I wiſh to my Accuſers and Proſecutors who have
purſued my blood, That I might meet their ſouls in Heaven.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>I ſhall divide my Speech into three parts; ſpeak ſomething concerning my
Charge, and a word concerning my Accuſers, and touching my Judges, without
any animoſity at all, and then ſomething concerning my ſelf for my own vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and then a word of Exhortation; and ſo I ſhall commit my ſoul to God.</p>
               <p>Concerning my Charge, it is black and hideous, many things falſly ſuggeſted,
but nothing capital ſufficiently proved by any one act, that I am conſcious to my
ſelf, proved againſt me that I did. The Charge was high and full, but the Proof
empty and low: Though there were eight Witneſſes that came in againſt me; yet
none of them did prove, That ever I writ any Letter, or directed any man to
write a Letter into <hi>Scotland</hi> or into Forreign parts: No man proved, That I
ſent away any Letter, that I received any Letter, that I collected, or gave, or
lent any Money to aſſiſt or promote the Scotiſh War. This is all that was ſworn
againſt me, That I was preſent when Letters were read, that I made a motion
for Money to give to <hi>Maſſey;</hi> ſo that Beloved, my preſence at, and concealment of
Letters that were received and ſent from Forreign parts.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115116:10"/>
                  <hi>There being a diſturbance amongſt the people, he ſaid,</hi> I am amuſed, I
muſt break off, things are true.</p>
               <p>But the tumult being appeaſed, he went on, ſaying,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <p>As concerning my Accuſers I ſhall not ſay much, I do forgive them, and I
pray God forgive them alſo; yet what the Evangeliſt obſerves concerning Chriſts
Accuſers, I may without vanity or falſhood ſay of mine, that they did not agree
among themſelves; yea not onely contradicting one another, but ſometimes a
Witneſs contradict himſelf. And though their Teſtimony did condemn my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
yet I have condemned their Teſtimony; and truly there are many remarkable
Circumſtances that I might take notice of, either in, or before, or ſince the Trial,
that might be worthy obſervation; but I will not inſiſt upon them, onely in the
general; I will name none of them, in the general ſome of them have ſent to me
to pray me to forgive them the wrong they have done me. One of them hath
written to me under his own hand, to pray me to forgive him the wrong he hath
done me; And told me withal, That that day that I ſhould die a violent death, his
life would be no comfort to him, becauſe he was an Inſtrument in taking away
mine. Others of my witneſſes, they were ſome terrified before they would teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie,
ſome hired, ſome fined before they would bear witneſs againſt me, but I will
forgive them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII.</head>
               <p>As concerning my Judges, I will not judge them, and yet I will not juſtifie
them, I believe (I will ſay but this of them) That what moved <hi>(John Baptiſt</hi>
what moved) <hi>Herod</hi> to cut off <hi>John Baptiſts</hi> head, moved them to cut off mine,
and that was for his Oaths ſake <hi>John Baptiſt [meaning</hi> Herod] to avoid perjury,
he would commit murther, whereas if <hi>John Baptiſts</hi> head had been upon his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
he would have been guilty of neither.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
               <p>I have ſomething in the ſecond place to speak concerning my ſelf, and then I
ſhall come briefly to a Concluſion. Concerning my ſelf, I have gone through va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
reports: There are many Sons of ſlander, whoſe mouths are as open Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres
to bury my Name before my friends can bury my body. My comfort is,
there will be a Reſurrection of Names as well as Bodies at the laſt Day;
God will not onely wipe off tears from mine eyes this day, but wipe off all blots and
reproaches from my Name before many days be over; And though my Body will
ſoon rot under ground, yet my hope is, my Name will not rot above it: I am not
ignorant what Calumnies are caſt upon me, and more likely to be after I am
dead and gone. The very night before my intended Execution the laſt moneth,
there was an inſulting Letter written to me to tell me, that after I was dead there
ſhould be ſomething publiſhed against me to my ſhame; I hope you will have ſo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115116:11"/>
much charity as not to believe Reproaches caſt upon a dead man, who will be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
in the grave, and not able to ſpeak a word in his own juſtification. I am aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
both as to my Practices, and as to my Principles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IX.</head>
               <p>I ſhall begin with the firſt: There are five Asperſions as to my practices that
are laid upon me; Firſt, That I am a Lyar, that I am an Extortioner, that I am
an Adulterer, that I am a Murtherer, and that I am a turbulent perſon; crimes
ſcandalous in any man, but much more abominable in a Miniſter.</p>
               <p>Now I hope you will believe a dying man, who dare not look God in the face
with a lye in his mouth. I am accuſed of lying, that what I denied before the
High Court of Juſtice, that afterwards I ſhould confeſs, or elſe was proved againſt
me: Now in the preſence of God I tell you, as I would confeſs nothing that was
criminal, ſo I did deny nothing that was true, and that I might ſeal it to you with
my blood; what I did deny, the proteſtations I made before the High Court, I
make them briefly now, That I never writ Letter to the King, Queen,
Church or State of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or to any particular perſon of the Scotiſh Nation
ſince the Wars began to this day: That I never received any Letter writ to me,
either from the King, or from the Queen, or from the Church or State of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
or from any particular perſon of the Scotiſh Nation ſince the Wars began
to this day: That I never collected, gave or lent one peny of money, either to the
King, Queen, Church or State of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or to any particular perſon to ſend
into <hi>Scotland,</hi> to any particular perſon of the Scotiſh Nation to this day. It is true,
I confeſſed though it was not proved, and happily upon that ground the miſtake
might riſe, I did give money to <hi>Maſſey,</hi> but he is of the Engliſh not of the Scotiſh
Nation, and I did write a Letter to him, but he is of the Engliſh not of the Scotiſh
Nation. That for which I here come, is for moving onely for money for him, and
for being preſent when Letters were read from him and others; and I am ſo far
(though man hath condemned me) from thinking that either God or my own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
condemns me for a ſin in what I am condemned for, that God and my own
Conſcience acquits me; and what I ſaid at the Bar when I received my Sentence
that now is to be executed, I ſhall ſay now upon the Scaffold, That for the things
I am condemned, neither doth God nor my own Conſcience condemn me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECT. X.</head>
               <p>The next particular, I am accuſed to be an Extortioner, and this is in the
mouths, I am loth to name them becauſe I would not ſhew rancor, but I am char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
as if I ſhould be a grievous Extortioner, to receive 30 l. for the loan of 300.
beſides 8 l. in the hundred for intereſt, which in the preſence of God, and of you all,
I do declare to you, is a moſt notorious and an abominable falſhood. I am accuſed
likewiſe to be an Adulterer: and that this Report it is not in the mouths of mean
men, but in the mouths of thoſe that ſit at ſtern, as if I were a debauched perſon,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115116:11"/>
and were guilty of uncleanneſs. Now I tell you through the grace of God, as <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
ſaid of himſelf in another caſe, <hi>That he was not tempted to Covetouſneſs,</hi>
through the grace of God I can ſay, I was not tempted in all my life to unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.
It doth not much grieve me though theſe ſlanders lye upon me: I know my
betters have been worſe accuſed before me. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> he was accuſed by two har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets
that he had committed folly with them, and yet the man was chaſte and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.
<hi>Beza</hi> was charged not onely of Drunkenneſs, but of Laſciviouſneſs alſo,
and many others have been accuſed with the ſame, if not worſe ſlanders then I
have been.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XI.</head>
               <p>But that which goes neareſt my heart, I am accuſed to be a Murtherer alſo,
and this is a Charge high indeed; I am charged with the guilt of all the Blood of
<hi>Scotland,</hi> whereas if I did lie under the guilt of one drop of blood, I could not look
upon you with ſo chearful a Countenance, and I could not be filled with ſo peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
a Heart and Conſcience as I am at this day, I bleſs my God I am free from
the blood of all: indeed thoſe who lay this to my charge, they do to me as <hi>Nero</hi>
did to the Chriſtians, he put <hi>Rome</hi> on fire, and then charged the Chriſtians with
it: ſo they put <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> into a flame, and yet charge me with the
guilt of that Blood, who have poured tears to God night and day to quench the
burning which ſome mens Ambition and Luſts have kindled. I would fain know
of any man what act it is I have done, what was it was proved in the High Court
againſt me to make me guilty of <hi>Scotland's</hi> blood? Did I ever invite the Scots to
invade <hi>England?</hi> what man did lay that to my charge? Did I ever encourage
our Engliſh Army to invade <hi>Scotland?</hi> what action is it that I have done that
makes me guilty of the blood? Indeed this I have done, and this I own, and this
I ſtand to; I have as a private man prayed unto God many a day, and kept many
a Faſt, wherein I have ſought God, that there might be an Agreement between
the King and the Scots upon the intereſt of Religion, and the terms of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.
Now by what conſequence can this be ſtrained to charge me with <hi>Scotland's</hi>
blood? For my part, I was but onely at one Meeting where that Question was
propoſed (Faſts onely excepted) what ſhould be thought fit to be done to promote
the Agreement between the King and the Scots, and that was moved in my houſe,
and to that end when there were ſome things there produced which they called a
<hi>Commiſſion</hi> and <hi>Inſtructions</hi> to ſend to <hi>Holland;</hi> as ſoon as ever I heard them,
I did declare againſt them: I did declare that private perſons, it was an act of
high preſumption for private perſons to commiſſionate, and an act of notorious falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood
to ſay, it was in the Name of the Preſbyterian Party, when none knew of it as
I know, but onely thoſe few that were then preſent. Now this is onely a politique
Engine to make the Presbyterian Party odious, who are the beſt friends to a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered
Government of any ſort of people in the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115116:12"/>
               <head>SECT. XII.</head>
               <p>I am accuſed likewiſe to be a man of a turbulent ſpirit, to be an enemy to the
Peace and Quiet of the Nation. Now to this I would be judged, let my Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational
and my Domeſtical Relations judge for me, whether I am not a man that
would fain have lived quiet in the Land: I am, as <hi>Jeremy</hi> was, born a man of
contention, not actively, I contend, I ſtrive with none, but paſſively, many ſtrive
and contend with me; God is my witneſs, my judgement hath put me upon endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors
after all honorable and juſt ways, for peace and love among the godly. The
grief of my heart hath been for the Diviſion, and the deſire of my ſoul for a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion
amongſt Gods People. And when I ſpeak of a union, I would not be miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood:
I do not mean a State-union to engage to the preſent Power, that is againſt
my Principle, that is to ſay, a Confederacy with them that ſay a Confederacy, that
is rather a Combination then a Gospel-union. Thoſe who have gotten Power into
their hands by Policy, and uſe it by Cruelty, they will loſe it with Ignominy.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sher. <hi>Titchhurn.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p> Sir, be modeſt: I am not able to endure this, indeed I am
not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Love.</speaker>
                  <p> Sir, I ſhall look God in the face with what I ſay. (Beloved) I am afraid of
your <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion which I plead for, <hi>to wit,</hi> a Church-union (I am ſtopped in many
things) a Church union, <hi>to wit,</hi> love among the Godly. This is it the deſires of
my ſoul have been ever for, that thoſe that fear God might walk hand in hand
in the fellowſhip of the Gospel, both in truth and love: if this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion be not, I
am afraid through our diviſions a company of looſe Libertines will riſe, who will
endeavor not onely to overthrow Doctrines of Faith and Religion and Maners
<hi>(but then correcting himſelf, he ſaid)</hi> Doctrines of Faith and the power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,
but even good Maners alſo. I remember an obſervation of Holy <hi>Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
giving his judgement upon the State of <hi>England,</hi> he ſaid thus, <hi>There is a
great fear of Popery coming into</hi> England; I fear that too; but I fear more the
coming of Atheiſm into <hi>England,</hi> then the coming in of Popery; and truly that
is my fear alſo. Thus as to my practices.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIII.</head>
               <p>A word now as to my Principles.</p>
               <p>I am accuſed to be an Apoſtate, to be a Turn-coat, to be this, to be that,
to be any thing, but what I am. In the General I will tell you, That I bleſs my
God, an High Court, a long Sword, a bloody Scaffold, hath not made me in the
leaſt to alter my Principles, or to wrong my Conſcience. And that I might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
to you my Principles, I hope I ſhall do it with freedom; I will iritate and
provoke none; what I ſhall ſay, ſhall not be an iritation, or provocation of others,
(at leaſt not intended by me) but onely as a genuine and clear Manifeſtation of
my Principles how they ſtand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Then my Principles; As to Civil and Religious Affairs, I declare, That
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115116:12"/>
I die with my Judgement ſet againſt Malignity, I do hate both name and thing;
I ſtill retain as vehement a deteſtation of a Malignant Intereſt, as ever I did;
yet I would not be miſunderſtood: I do not count the Godly party, our Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Brethren in <hi>Scotland,</hi> I do not count them a Malignant party; nor their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending
their Nation, and Title to their King, to be a Malignant Intereſt, but
an honeſt and a juſtifiable Cauſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> I am of this Judgement (though I am againſt Malignity) yet I
am not againſt, but for, a Regulated Monarchy; a mixt Monarchy, as ours
was, I judge to be one of the beſt Governments in the world: I did (it is true)
oppoſe in my Place and Calling, the Forces of the late King, and were he alive
again, and ſhould I live longer, the Cauſe being as then it was, I ſhould oppoſe
him longer. I did oppoſe his Forces, but never was againſt the Office: I do as
much hate Court Paraſites, who would ſcrew up Monarchy into Tyranny, as thoſe
who pull it down to bring in Anarchy: I was never.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I was never for putting the King to death, whoſe Perſon I did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
in my Covenant to preſerve. It is true, I did in my Place and Calling, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
his Forces, but I did never endeavor to deſtroy his Perſon. There is a
ſcandal raiſed of me, That in a Sermon at <hi>Windſor</hi> I ſhould have theſe words,
<hi>[That it would never be well with</hi> England, <hi>till the King were let blood upon
the Neck-Vein]</hi> Which in the preſence of God, and of you all, I never ſpake
ſuch words, as relating to him, though my judgement then was, and ſtill is, for
bringing Malignants, who did ſeduce him and draw him from the Parliament,
to condign puniſhment. I deem it an ill way to cure the Body Politique, by cutting
off the Political Head.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I die with my Judgement not ſatisfied to take the Ingagement, I
pray God forgive them that impoſe it, and ſubſcribe it, and preſerve thoſe that
refuſe it.</p>
               <p>I would not (in the next place) be looked upon (now I am a dying man) I
would not be looked upon as a man owning this preſent Government, I die with
my Judgement againſt it. It is true, in a Caſe of Life, I did Petition the preſent
Power, and did give them the Titles they take to themſelves, and other men give
them; but herein I did not wrong, nor croſs my Principles: There are many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances
in the Scripture to juſtifie this; <hi>Huſhai</hi> did give the Title to <hi>Abſolon,</hi>
though <hi>Abſolon</hi> had no right to the Title: <hi>David</hi> was the lawful King, and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
himſelf gave him the Title as well as <hi>Huſhai:</hi> And <hi>Calvin</hi> he gave a Title
to the <hi>French</hi> King, calling him <hi>Rex Chriſtianiſſimus,</hi> The moſt Chriſtian King;
yet he knew he was a Papiſt: And we gave a Title to King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, to
call him, <hi>The Defender of the Faith;</hi> and yet he had no right to the Title; he
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115116:13"/>
was an Oppoſer, not a Defender of the Faith: The Title was given him upon an
evil ground, becauſe he oppoſed the Faith; he oppoſed the Doctrine of <hi>Luther,</hi>
and therefore the Pope gave him that Title <hi>[The Defender of the Faith]</hi> and
yet none did ſcruple to give him the Title that was then commonly given him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVI.</head>
               <p>In the next place, I diſcover my Judgement; I provoke none, onely tell you
what my own thoughts are, That ſo after I am dead and gone, I might not be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied;
for I dare not now bely my Principles: My Judgement is againſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion
of the Scotiſh Nation by our Engliſh Army: They who gave us a friendly
Aſſiſtance, who were joyned with us in the ſame Covenant, who drew a Sword
with us in the ſame Quarrel; ſhould I live a thouſand years, I ſhould never
draw a Sword againſt them in all my life. <hi>Scotland</hi> may ſay as it was ſaid of
<hi>Edom, The men of my Confederacy that were at Peace with me, have riſen
up againſt me, deceived me and prevailed againſt me.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Scotland</hi> will
not be a Commonwealth, they ſhall not be a people; becauſe they will not break
Covenants, ſome men would have them broken; becauſe they will not lay their
Conſciences waſte, their Land muſt be laid waſte.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> And ſo I have done, onely with a word of Exhortation. I die cleaving
to all thoſe Oaths, Vows, Covenants and Proteſtations, that were impoſed by the
Two Houſes of Parliament, as owning them, and dying with my Judgement for
them: The Vow and Covenant, The Proteſtation, The Solemn League and
Covenant: And this I tell you all, I had rather die a Covenant keeper, then live
a Covenant breaker.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVII.</head>
               <p>I have onely, now I am come to the third and laſt part of my Speech, and ſo
I ſhall have done, and commit my Soul unto God who gave it, My Exhortation,
it ſhall be to this great City; unto the Godly Miniſtry of it, and unto my own
Congregation, from whom death hath parted me, which nothing elſe could.</p>
               <p>To the City, I wiſh an affluence and a confluence of all Bleſſings upon it;
and yet I fear gray hairs, as the Symptoms of a Declenſion, are here and there up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
it; yet ſhe knows it not. O <hi>London, London!</hi> God is ſtaining the pride of all
thy Glory; thy Glory is flying away like a Bird; contempt of the Miniſtry;
oppoſition againſt Reformation; general Apoſtacy; Covenant breaking hath
brought <hi>London</hi> low, and I fear will bring it lower: I tremble to think what
evils are coming upon it. This City, it is the Receptacle of all Errors, That as
your Commodities have been vented and ſpread from hence into every corner of
the Land, ſo hath Hereſies and Blasphemies had their firſt riſe from this great
and populous City, and ſpread into all the Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVIII.</head>
               <p>To the Inhabitants of this City, I commend but theſe few Particulars.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115116:13"/>
Firſt, Let me beg you to love your painful and your godly Miniſters, if they be
taken away, you are like to have worſe come in their rooms: I know the Preſbyterian
Miniſters are the great eye-ſore, who have formerly been counted the Chariots,
and the Horſmen of Iſrael. But I will ſay to <hi>London,</hi> as was ſaid to <hi>Leyden,</hi> That
after <hi>Junius</hi> was taken away (an Orthodox Miniſter) <hi>Arminius</hi> that peſtilent
Heretick came in his room; if your godly Miniſters (as there are ten already at
one blow taken from you) if they be taken away, Arminians, Anabaptiſts, nay
Jeſuits are like to ſupply their rooms, if God in mercy prevent not.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Submit your ſelves to Church-Government, that would lay a curb
and reſtraint upon your luſts, it is a golden, and an eaſie yoke, to which if you do not
ſubmit, God may lay an heavier, an iron yoke upon your necks.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIX.</head>
               <p>Thirdly, Take heed of thoſe Doctrines that come under the Notion of New
Lights; I have judged that thoſe Doctrines you ought to ſuspect whether they be
true, when the brocher of them ſaith it is New; for Truth, it is as old as the
Bible: A remarkable paſſage I would ſuggeſt unto you, in <hi>Deut. 32.</hi> it is ſaid
there, <hi>They choſe them new gods,</hi> that were newly sprung up; what were theſe
new gods? the next words tell you, they were old devils, <hi>they ſacrificed to devils,
not to God:</hi> Now their <hi>Sacrificing</hi> to the old Devil, it was called a <hi>Sacrificing</hi>
(to deceive the People) to new gods that were newly come up; new gods, they were
but the old devils: So I ſay of many of thoſe things that go under the notion of
New Lights, it is but old darkneſs, old Hereſies raked out of the Dunghil, which
were buried in former ages in the Church, with contempt and reproach many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
years ago. Again,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XX.</head>
               <p>Fourthly, Bewail your great loſs that you have in the taking away of ſo many
Miniſters out of your City: there are ten Miniſters (if I miſtake not) that are
taken away and removed in one blow; thoſe who were burning and ſhining Lights
in their ſeveral Candleſticks, and bright Stars in their ſeveral Orbs; though I
am not worthy of the world, therefore I am taken out of it; yet as for my ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Brethren who are now in Bonds and Baniſhment, the world is not worthy of
them.</p>
               <p>Again, in the next place, take heed how you be forward in ingaging in a War
with your godly Brethren in the Scotiſh Nation; for my part, I have oppoſed the
Tyranny of a King, but I never oppoſed the Title: take heed what you do.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXI.</head>
               <p>I have ſomething in the next place to ſpeak to the godly Miniſtery of this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
were it not that I were a dying man, I would not ſpeak to ſuch reverend and
grave men; I would, as <hi>Elihu</hi> being but a yong man, I would ſay, <hi>Multitudes
of years ſhould teach wiſdom,</hi> and I would hold my tongue; but the words of a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115116:14"/>
dying man take, whether they be diſcreet or no, or ſo well ordered and managed or
no; for them, I would firſt deſire God to ſhew them mercy, they that have begged
for mercy for me at the day of my death, I will beg but this of them, That as they
have not been aſhamed of my Chain, ſo they would now wax confident by my
Bonds and by my Blood; I know they are maligned and threatned, yet my Prayer
is for them, that in <hi>Acts 4. 29. Now Lord, behold their threatnings, and
grant that thy Servants may Preach thy word with all boldneſs:</hi> Though I am
but yong, yet I will offer my yong experience to my grave Fathers and Brethren,
and that is this; Now I am to dye, I have abundant peace in my own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
that I have ſet my ſelf againſt the Sins and Apoſtacies of this preſent Age:
It is true, my faithfulneſs hath procured me ill will from men, but it hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed
me peace with God, I have lived in peace, and I ſhall dye in peace: That
which I have to beſeech of the Miniſters, is this, To beg them to keep up Church-Government:
Whatſoever God doth with the Governments of the world, turning
Kingdoms upſide down, yet the Government of the Church will ſtand; And of
all Governments, I dye with this perſwaſion, That the Preſbyterial Government
makes moſt for Purity and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity throughout the Churches of the Saints: I would
beg them therefore to keep up Church-Government; That they would not let their
Elderſhips fall; That they would take heed of too general Admiſſions to the
Lords-Supper; That they be not too prodigal of the Blood of Chriſt, by too ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
Admiſsions of men to partake of the Supper, that Sealing Ordinance:
And now I am ſpeaking to them, I ſhall ſpeak a word of them, and ſo I have
done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXII.</head>
               <p>I have heard many clamors ſince I came to Priſon, as if that Plot (which it is
called) that I am condemned for, as if all the City Miniſters they were engaged
in this Deſign, which as a dying man I tell you, That all the Miniſters that were
preſent at the meeting, and had a hand in that buſineſs for which I am to be
put to death, all thoſe Miniſters, they are either in Priſon, or they are diſcovered
already; and therefore, I do here upon my death free the Miniſters of the City,
That thoſe who are not yet in trouble, nor diſcovered to the Committee of Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations,
none of them had a hand in that buſineſs in which I was ingaged, in
which my conſcience doth tell me I have not ſinned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXIII.</head>
               <p>I have now (I have done immediatly, for I would fain be at my Fathers houſe)
but a word to ſpeak to my own Congregation, and I do return praiſes unto God, and
thanksgiving unto him, for the love I have had from them; I found them a ſolid
and a judicious people, and many of them Religious: The Miniſtery of that
learned man Mr. <hi>Anthony Burges</hi> did much good amongſt them, though I have
cauſe to be humbled, my weak Miniſtery did but little; they afforded me a great
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115116:14"/>
deal of love, and a liberal maintenance: And this is all I deſire of them, That
they would chuſe a godly, learned, and an Orthodox Miniſter to ſucceed; it
would be a great comfort to me before I go to Heaven, if I had this perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
that a learned, Orthodox, godly man ſhould fill that Pulpit. And for
encouragement to any godly Miniſter, whoſe lot it ſhall be to ſucceed me, I
will ſay this to him, That he will have as comfortable a livelihood, and as
loving a people, as any people in <hi>London,</hi> a few only excepted;) I had as much
ſatisfaction amongst them, as ever I had in any condition in all my life, and
ſhould never have parted from them, had not now death parted us, to which
I do ſubmit with all Chriſtian meekneſs and cheerfulneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXIV.</head>
               <p>I am now drawing to an end of my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>peech, and to an end of my life to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether:
But before I do expire my laſt breath, I ſhall deſire to juſtifie God,
and to condemn my ſelf. Here I come to that which you call an untimely end,
and a ſhameful death; but bleſſed be God, it is my glory, and it is my comfort; I
ſhall juſtifie God; he is righteous, becauſe I have ſinned; he is righteous,
though he doth cut me off in the midſt of my days, and in the midſt of my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry.
I cannot complain that Complaint in the Pſalmiſt, in the 44 <hi>Pſalm,
Thou ſelleſt thy people for nought, and doſt not increaſe thy wealth by their
price.</hi> My blood it ſhall not be ſpilt for nought; I may do more good by my death,
then by my life, and glorifie God more in dying upon a Scaffold, then if I had dyed
of a Diſeaſe upon my bed. I bleſs my God I have not the leaſt trouble upon
my ſpirit; but I dye with as much quietneſs of mind, lie down I hope I ſhall
upon the Block, as if I were going to lie down upon my Bed to take my reſt.
I ſee men hunger after my fleſh, and thirſt after my blood, which will hasten
my happineſs, and their ruine, and greaten their guilt: For though I am a
man of an obſcure Family, of mean Parentage, ſo that my blood is not as the
blood of Nobles; yet I will ſay, mine is a Chriſtians blood, a Miniſters blood,
yea it is innocent blood alſo: My blood, my body, my dead body, it will be a
morſel which I believe will hardly be digeſted, and my blood it will be bad
food for this Infant Commonwealth (as Mr <hi>Prideaux</hi> called it) for this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant
Commonwealth to ſuck on: Mine is not Malignant blood, though here
I am brought as a grievous and a notorious Offender.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXV.</head>
               <p>Now Beloved, I ſhall not only juſtifie God (as I do without a Complement,)
for he is very Just, that my Priſon was not my Hell, that this Scaffold is not
the bottomleſs pit, I have deſerved both, I have deſerved it: I do not only
juſtifie God, but I deſire this day to magnifie God, to magnifie the riches of his
glorious grace, that ſuch a one as I, born in an obſcure Country in <hi>Wales,</hi> of
obſcure Parents, that God ſhould look upon me, and ſingle me out from among
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115116:15"/>
all my kinred, ſingle me out to be an Object of his everlaſting Love; that when
for the first fourteen years of my life I never heard a Sermon, and yet in the
fifteenth year of my life, God through his grace did convert me: And I here
ſpeak it without vanity (what ſhould a dying man be proud of?) for theſe
twenty years, though I am accuſed of many ſcandalous evils, I ſpeak it to
the praiſe and glory of my God, for theſe twenty years God hath kept me, I
have not fallen into a ſcandalous ſin; I have laboured to keep a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
from my youth up: I magnifie his grace, that he hath not only made me
a Christian, but made me a Miniſter, judged me faithful, and put me into the
Ministry; and though the Office be troden upon, and be diſgraced, yet it is
my glory, that I dye a despiſed Miniſter: I had rather be a Preacher in a
Pulpit, then a Prince upon a Throne; I had rather be an Inſtrument to bring
Souls to Heaven, then to have all the Nations to bring in tribute to me. I
am not only a Chriſtian, and a Preacher, but, what ever men judg me, I am a
Martyr too, I ſpeak it without vanity: Would I have renounced my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
and debauched my Conſcience, and ventured my Soul, there might have
been more hopes of ſaving my life, that I ſhould not have come to this place:
but bleſſed be my God, I have made the best choyce, I have choſe affliction ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
then Sin; and therefore welcome Scaffold, and welcome Ax, and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
Death, welcome Block, welcome all, becauſe it will ſend me to my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
Houſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXVI.</head>
               <p>I have great cauſe to magnifie Gods Grace, that he hath ſtood by me du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
my impriſonment: It hath been a time of no little temptation to me;
and yet, bleſſed be his grace, he hath ſtrengthened, and ſtood by me: I mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
his grace, that though now I come to dye a violent death, yet that death
is not a terror to me; through the blood of ſprinkling the fear of Death is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
out of my heart: God is not a terror to me, therefore Death is not dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
to me. I bleſs my God (I ſpeak it without vanity) I have formerly had
more fear in the drawing of a tooth, then now I have in the cutting off my
Head. I was for ſome years, five or ſix, under a ſpirit of bondage, and did
fear Death exceedingly; but then when the fear of Death was upon me,
Death was not neer me: but now Death is neer me, (bleſſed be my Saviour)
he hath the ſting of Death in his own ſides, and ſo makes the grave a bed of
reſt to me; and makes Death, the laſt Enemy, to be a friend, though he be a
grim friend. I bleſs God further, that though I am to be caſt out of the world;
I bleſs my God, though men judg me to be caſt out of the world; yet that
God hath not caſt me out of the hearts and prayers of his people. I had rather
be caſt out of the world, then be caſt out of the heart of any godly man. Some
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115116:15"/>
think me (it is true) not worthy to live, and yet others judg, I do not deſerve
to dye; but God will judg all men, I will judg none.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXVII.</head>
               <p>I have now done; I have no more to ſay, but to deſire the help of all your
prayers, that God would give me the continuance and ſupply of divine grace
to carry me through this great work that I am now to do; That I, who am to
do a work I never did, I may have a ſtrength that I never had; That I may
put off this Body with as much quietneſs and comfort of minde, as ever I put
off my clothes to go to bed. And now I am to commend my Soul to God, and
to receive my fatal blow: I am comforted in this, though men kill me, they
cannot damn me; and though they thruſt me out of the world, yet they cannot
ſhut me out of Heaven. I am now going to my long home, and you are going
to your ſhort homes: but I will tell you, I ſhall be at home before you; I ſhall
be at Heaven, my Fathers houſe, before you will be at your own Houſes. Now
I am going to the Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to the innumerable company of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,
to Jeſus Chriſt the Mediator of the new Covenant, to the ſpirits of all
men made perfect, to God the judg of all; in whoſe preſence there is fulneſs
of joy, and at whoſe right hand there are pleaſures for evermore.</p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude.</p>
               <p>But then Mr Sheriff <hi>Tichburn</hi> telling him, that the words were, <hi>the ſpirits
of juſt men made perfect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Love. <hi>He then corrected himſelf, ſaying,</hi> To the ſpirits of juſt men made
perfect, and to God the Judg of all; in whoſe preſence there is fulneſs of joy,
and in whoſe right hand there are pleaſures for evermore.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXVIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I conclude with that ſpeech of the Apoſtle:</hi> I am now <hi>(in</hi> 2 Tim. 4. 6, 7. I
am now) to be offered up, and the time of my departure is at hand; <hi>but</hi> I
have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the Faith; Henceforth there is a crown
of righteouſneſs layd up for me; and not for me onely, but for all them that
love the appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>through whoſe blood (when I
have ſhed my blood) I expect Salvation, and remiſſion of ſins. And ſo the
Lord bleſs you all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then turning to Mr Sheriff, he ſaid;</p>
               <p>May I pray?</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sheriff <hi>Tichburn.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p> Yes: but conſider the time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Love.</speaker>
                  <p> I have done Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then turning to the people, he ſaid;</hi> Beloved, I will but pray a little
while with you, to commend my Soul to God, and I have done.</p>
               <p>Then Mr <hi>Aſh</hi> told him:</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr <hi>Aſh.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p> The Houſe is riſen, and therefore—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115116:16"/>
                  <speaker>Love.</speaker>
                  <p> To which Mr <hi>Love</hi> anſwered, <hi>I, I, Sir.</hi> 
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <p>After which he prayed
with an audible voyce, ſaying,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXIX.
M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Love's Prayer.</head>
               <p>MOſt Glorious and Eternal Majeſty, Thou art righteous and holy in all
thou dost to the ſons of men; though thou haſt ſuffered men to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn
thy ſervant, thy ſervant will not condemn thee; He juſtifieth thee,
though thou cutteſt him off in the midſt of his days, and in the midſt of his
Miniſtry; bleſſing thy glorious Name, that though his name be taken away
from the Land of the Living, that yet he is not blotted out of the Book of the
Living. Father, my hour is come; thy poor creature can ſay without va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
and falſhood, he hath deſired to glorifie thee upon Earth; glorifie thou
now him in Heaven. He hath deſired to bring the Souls of other men to
Heaven; let his Soul be brought to Heaven. O thou bleſſed God, whom
thy Creature hath ſerved, who hath made thee his hope, and his confidence
from his youth; forſake him not, now he is drawing nigh to thee; now he is
in the valley of the ſhadow of death, Lord be thou life to him; ſmile thou up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
him, while men frown on him. Lord, thou haſt ſetled this perſwaſion in his
heart, That as ſoon as ever the blow is given, to divide his Head from his
Body, he ſhall be united to his Head in Heaven. Bleſſed be God that thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant
dyes in thoſe hopes. Bleſſed be God, that thou haſt filled the ſoul of thy
ſervant with joy and peace in beleeving. O Lord, think upon that poor Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of mine, that is a companion in tribulation with me, who is this day to
loſe his life as well as I: O fill him full of the joy of the Holy Ghoſt, when he
is to give up the ghoſt: Lord, ſtrengthen our hearts, that we may give up the
ghoſt with joy, and not with grief. We intreat thee, O Lord, think upon thy
poor Churches: O that <hi>England</hi> might live in thy ſight; and O that <hi>London</hi>
might be a faithful City to thee; that righteouſneſs might be amongst them:
that ſo peace and plenty may be within their walls, and righteouſneſs within
their habitation. Lord, heal the breaches of this poor Nation. Make <hi>England</hi>
and <hi>Scotland</hi> as one ſtaff in the Lords hand; that <hi>Ephraim</hi> might not envy
<hi>Judah,</hi> nor <hi>Judah</hi> vex <hi>Ephraim;</hi> but that both might flee upon the ſhoulders
of the <hi>Philiſtins:</hi> that men of the Proteſtant Religion, engaged in the ſame
Cauſe and Covenant, might not delight to ſpill each others blood, but might
engage againſt the common Adverſaries of our Religion and Liberties. God
ſhew mercy to all that fear him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115116:16"/>
               <head>SECT. XXX.</head>
               <p>Think upon our Covenant-keeping Brethren in the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi>
keep them faithful to thee, and let not them that have invaded them over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spread
their whole Land: Prevent the ſhedding of more Chriſtian Blood, if
it ſeem good in thine eyes. God, ſhew mercy to thy poor Servant who is here
now giving up the ghost. O bleſſed Jeſus, apply thy Blood, not only for my
Juſtification unto life, but alſo for my comfort, for the quieting of my Soul,
that ſo I might be in the joys of Heaven before I come to a poſſeſſion of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.
Hear the prayers of all thy people that have been made for thy Servant:
and though thou haſt denyed prayer as to the particular requeſt concerning my
life, yet let herein the fruit of prayer be ſeen, that thou wilt bear up my heart
againſt the fear of death. God ſhew mercy to all that fear him: Shew mercy
to all that have engaged for the life of thy Servant, let them have mercy at
the day of their appearing before Jeſus Christ. Preſerve thou a godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry
in this Nation, and reſtore a godly Miniſtry, and cauſe yet good days to
be the heritage of thy people, for the Lords ſake. Now Lord into thy hands thy
Servant committeth his ſpirit: And though he may not with <hi>Steven</hi> ſee the
Heavens opened, let him have the Heavens opened; and though he may not
ſee upon a Scaffold the Son of God ſtanding at the right hand of God, yet let
him come to the glorified Body of Jeſus Chriſt, and this hour have an intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual
ſight of the glorified Body of his Saviour. Lord Jeſus receive my
ſpirit, and Lord Ieſus ſtand by me thy dying Servant, who hath endeavored in
his life time to ſtand for thee. Lord hear, pardon all his infirmities, wipe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
his iniquities by the blood of Chriſt, wipe off reproaches from his name,
wipe off guilt from his perſon, and receive him pure, and ſpotleſs, and blameleſs
before thee in love: And all this we beg for the ſake of Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen</hi>
and <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXXI.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr <hi>Aſh.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p> You make a Chriſtian end I hope.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr <hi>Love.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p> I, I, bleſs God.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then turning to Mr Sheriff</hi> Tichburn, <hi>ſaid,</hi> I thank you for this kindneſs;
Sir, you have expreſſed a great deal of kindneſs to me: Well, I go from a
Block to the boſom of my Saviour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then he asked,</hi> Where is the Executioner?</p>
               <p>When the Executioner came forward, he ſaid, <hi>Art thou the Officer?</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Executioner.</speaker>
                  <p> Yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Love.</speaker>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Then lifting up his eyes, he ſaid,</hi> O bleſſed Ieſus, that hath kept me
from the hurt of death, and from the fear of death. O bleſſed be God, bleſſed
be God.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115116:17"/>
And taking his leave of the Miniſters, he ſaid;</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Love.</speaker>
                  <p> The Lord be with you all. </p>
               </sp>
               <p>And taking leave of Sheriff <hi>Tichburn,</hi>
he kiſſed his hand.</p>
               <p>Then he kneeled down, and made a ſhort prayer privately.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then after riſing up, he ſaid,</hi> Bleſſed be God, I am full of joy and peace in
beleeving; I lie down with a world of comfort, as if I were to lie down in my
Bed. My Bed is but a ſhort ſleep, and this Death is a long ſleep, where I ſhall
reſt in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſom, and in the embraces of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
               <p>And then ſaying, <hi>The Lord bleſs you,</hi> he layd himſelf down upon the
Scaffold, with his Head ove the Block: And when he ſtretched forth his hands,
the <hi>Executioner</hi> cut off his Head at one blow.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="animadversions">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115116:17"/>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>THE
PREFACE
Briefly declaring the occaſion of the
ANIMADVERSIONS.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Roman Orator commendeth it as the property of a
good Orator, not onely to ſpeak things pertinent and
proper to his Cauſe for the promoting it, but alſo to
take heed of ſpeaking any thing that may prove preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial
to it. The great cauſe which Mr. <hi>Love</hi> both in
his life and at his death (at leaſt as himſelf inſinuates
over and over in his Diſcourſe enſuing) deſired above
all things to plead and promote, was the cauſe of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
Chriſt,</hi> and the ſalvation of the Souls of men. Now though I can eaſily
believe that he ſpake and taught many things in the time of his life, and ſome
things at the time of his death, which were and are of very good conſequence
towards the advancement of this Cauſe; yet I clearly finde him, partly by
what I read in the words uttered by him upon the Scaffold immediately before
his death, partly by what I have ſeen printed and publiſhed formerly, either
in his Name, or with his approbation and conſent, partly alſo by what I have
heard from ſome of his Sermons; that he was very defective in the property
of a good Orator mentioned, and that he was apt to ſpeak, not onely things
very impertinent and eccentrical to his Cauſe, but even ſuch things alſo (ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times)
which were of a manifeſt inconſiſtency with the Intereſt of it. I ſhall
(at preſent) onely give notice of ſuch Paſſages or Touches, which came from
him in his Speech or Prayer on the Scaffold, which are of a very prejudicial
import to that moſt honorable Cauſe of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and the Salvation of
men, to the promotion and maintenance whereof he profeſſeth himſelf to
have been ſo entirely devoted: that ſo what he acted or ſpake as a skilful
Workman, and was truly and really advantagious to his Cauſe, may have a
clear, entire and perfect operation in order hereunto, and not be incumbred,
foiled or impeded in their working by things of a contrary tendency and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
mixed with it. In this reſpect I truſt his Friends will finde no cauſe (I am
ſure will finde no juſt cauſe) of offence in that ſeparation of <hi>the vile from the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115116:18"/>
precious,</hi> which is intended in theſe Animadverſions; eſpecially conſidering,
that if Mr. <hi>Love</hi> himſelf were alive, with that Chriſtian ingenuity whereunto
he pretends once and again in this Diſcourſe, he could not but accept it as a
Service of love and faithfulneſs, for any man to ſtrengthen thoſe things which
are worthy and good in him, by diſabling and weakning that which is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe:
However, it is not meet nor of any good conſiſtence with thoſe ſacred
Reſpects which are due from every man unto mankinde, to tempt the living
unto folly, by giving honor unto the dead. Better it is that Mr. <hi>Love</hi>'s re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
ſhould be a little clouded, then that it ſhould glare in the weak eyes
of men to make them blinde: As for men of clear intellectuals and compoſed
judgements, Mr. <hi>Love</hi>s Speech might without the leaſt danger of tempting
them, have been preſented naked; there being nothing in it but what is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent
enough to ſuch men: Onely perſons of effeminate and enſlaved ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions
may poſſibly conceit, that they ſee viſions of worth and excellence,
where there is nothing but darkneſs and deceit, and ſo may receive dangerous
impreſſions from what they think they ſee, if their eyes be not anointed with
ſome eye-ſalve of ſuch an interpretation, which ſhall bring forth that which is
within the veyl, into the outer and open Court of the Temple.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>ANIMADVERSION upon Sect. I.</head>
               <p>IN this firſt Section, we have a firſt-fruits of Mr. <hi>Love</hi>'s Confidence in his
death, together with a taſte of that pleaſant Fancy, on which (it ſeems) he
fed with much contentment whileſt he yet lived; <hi>viz.</hi> how honorable that
Death which he was now to ſuffer would be unto him, as wherein he ſhould
parallel thoſe great Worthies of heaven, <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt, Paul,</hi> and the <hi>Saints
beheaded</hi> in the <hi>Revelation.</hi> Far be it from me to envy either Mr. <hi>Love</hi>'s or
any other man's confidence in their death. The great Deſire and grand De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign
of my Soul is, to conſult (with the utmoſt of my endeavors) the <hi>Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi>
of men, yea of all men without exception, in, and at their death. But
though I envy no mans confidence in death, yet I confeſs I pity the confidence
of many at ſuch a time; yea I pity many ſurviving, fearing leſt the confidence
of ſome dying, ſhould prove a ſnare of death unto them. Mr. <hi>Love</hi>'s confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
upon the Scaffold my ſoul pitieth, having ſo many and ſuch pregnant
grounds of Reaſon in mine eyes to judge it, if not hollow and heartleſs, yet
bottomleſs and groundleſs; Yet I confeſs I pity thoſe more, who through ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance
of their grounds, live under much danger of being enſnared and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
in evil, by occaſion of the ſaid confidence: For when evil doers (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
the firſt-born of this generation, Traitors) ſhall without repentance, and
this ſome ways profeſſed, die full of confidence in God, whether real or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,
it is a ſore temptation upon men, not to be ſo tender or fearful of ſuch
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115116:18"/>
practices, as the hatred and high diſpleaſure of God againſt them, admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
them to be. Therefore, for the ſakes of ſuch perſons who are in danger of
being made confident in evil by Mr. <hi>Love</hi>'s confidence at his death, I ſhall
brief<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y account unto them the grounds of my great jealouſie and fear, that
this confidence was (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) <hi>in the face</hi> onely, and not in the
heart; or if in the heart, yet without any ſubſtantial or ſufficient ground for
the raiſing of it.</p>
               <p>1. The holy Ghoſt himſelf muſtereth <hi>Traitors, Heady, High-minded,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<hi>without natural affection,</hi> amongſt ſuch men who have <hi>[i. e.</hi> ſometimes have,
or may have] the <hi>Form of Godlineſs,</hi> and yet <hi>deny the power</hi> thereof. Now
though Mr. <hi>Love</hi> and his Abettors in their equivocal Dialect, wherein like
Canters, they uſe common and familiar words in uncouth and unknown ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications,
will not (it's like) call men of his [Mr. <hi>Love</hi>'s] practices and
ways, either <hi>Traitors, Heady, High-minded, without natural affection, &amp;c.</hi> yet
in the ordinary and beſt known ſignification of theſe terms, and in the ſenſe
wherein the holy Ghoſt uſeth them (unleſs they will quarrel our Engliſh
Tranſlation) he was both <hi>Traitor, Heady, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo look'd upon and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged,
by perſons who are not wont to pervert or wreſt words into by-ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications
to make the innocent guilty. I do not ſpeak now of the Parliament,
Councel of State, or High Court of Juſtice onely, but of all ſorts of perſons
in the Land, who have not either their hand or their heart in Mr. <hi>Love</hi>'s coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels
and practices. I mention thoſe whom the Apoſtle terms <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
natural affection,</hi> in reference to Mr. <hi>Love,</hi> becauſe it was the obſervation
of ſome who were preſent at his Execution from firſt to laſt, that though he
prayed for his fellow-Traitor and the Scots, not onely the profeſs'd, but highly
expreſt Enemies of his Countrey and Nation, yet he made not the leaſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
either of his wife or children, either in his Prayer or Diſcourſe. Now if
Mr. <hi>Love</hi> at his death was no better then a perſon having the <hi>Form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
but denying the power thereof,</hi> there was no good ground for that his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident
rejoycing therein.</p>
               <p>2. The Lord Chriſt ſaith expreſly, <hi>That if we forgive not men their treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
neither will our Heavenly Father forgive us our treſpaſſes.</hi> Now though
Mr. <hi>Love</hi> pretends fairneſs and clearneſs of ſpirit in this kinde again and
again, and that he brought no rancor or revengefulneſs of heart to the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold;
yet that he was inwardly full of this rottenneſs, his moſt venemous, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent,
falſe and bitter Inſinuations againſt the Parliament and State, uttered
upon the Scaffold, teſtifie to the face of his greateſt Advocates: See eſpecially
upon this account Sect. 12 where you will finde him ſo unchriſtianly, and with
ſuch inſufferable rancor and malice inveighing againſt the State, that one of
the preſent Magiſtrates, acknowledged by Mr. <hi>Love</hi> himſelf (and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115116:19"/>
cauſe) a good Friend of his, openly profeſſed that he was not able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure
it. Now if Mr. <hi>Love</hi> died upon ſuch terms, that his Heavenly Father
could not, according to his expreſly declared will, forgive him his treſpaſſes, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
he could have no ſufficient ground for that confidence which he expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
at his death.</p>
               <p>3. We read in Scripture of many confidences and rejoycings in men, and
theſe Profeſſors, without ſufficiency of ground to juſtifie or bear them out.
<hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of ſome who <hi>gloried</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>in the face,</hi> or in appearance, <hi>not
in the heart.</hi> And our Savior himſelf ſpeaketh of <hi>many, who</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>will
ſay unto him [i. e.</hi> think at preſent that they may with confidence ſay unto him]
<hi>in that</hi> [great] <hi>day, Lord, Lord, have we not propheſied in thy Name? and in
thy Name caſt out devils? and in thy Name done many wonderful works?</hi> To
whom notwithſtanding he will reply and profeſs, <hi>that he never knew them: De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part
from me ye that work iniquity,</hi> Mat. 7. 22, 23.</p>
               <p>4. Mr. <hi>Love</hi> did not, could not at his death out-confidence the ordinary
ſort of Papiſts, Prieſts and Jeſuits amongſt us, that have from time to time
drunk of the ſame cup with him (as well as <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> or <hi>Paul)</hi> and upon
the ſame account, in which particular <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſeparate from him
(as we ſhall ſee preſently) and leave him in the company of thoſe other.</p>
               <p>5. It is no very hard matter for a man ſtrongly acted and aſſiſted by a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
of popularity (a ſpirit with which Mr. <hi>Love</hi> hath been obſerved by many
to have been one ſpirit or fleſh rather, for many years paſt) to harden himſelf
againſt the fear of Death; to ſuppreſs, ſmother and keep under thoſe work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
of Nature and Conſcience, which ordinarily diſcover themſelves upon the
approaches of Death, in ſuch perſons who have no deſign to drive by the ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering
or ſuppreſſing of them; nor any collateral help or aid from any ſuch
ſpirit, to enable them to the ſubduing and vanquiſhing of them.</p>
               <p>6. Mr. <hi>Love</hi> (it is more then probable) was not onely vehemently exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
encouraged, importuned, but even ſolemnly by all the ſacred Intereſts of
high Presbytery, conjured by his Clergy-companions, to die like a valiant and
reſolute Champion of the Cauſe, and not to bewray the leaſt grudging of any
fear or repentance, for any thing he had acted upon the ſervice thereof; leſt
it ſhould be ſaid of Presbytery, <hi>Her glory was ſtained and betrayed by the cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardice
of her firſt-born.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seventhly (and laſtly) when I conſider theſe paſſages in Mr. <hi>Love</hi>'s Prayer,
<hi>[Sect. 30.] O bleſſed Jeſus, apply thy blood, not onely for my Juſtification unto
life, but alſo for the comfort, for the quieting of my Soul, that ſo I might be in
the joys of Heaven, before, &amp;c.</hi> And farther, <hi>Hear the Prayers of all thy people
that have been made for thy ſervant; and though thou haſt denied Prayer as to
the particular Requeſt concerning my life, yet let herein the fruit of prayer be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115116:19"/>
ſeen, that thou wilt bear up my heart againſt the fear of death;</hi> When (I ſay)
I ſeriouſly conſider the expreſs import of theſe paſſages, they raiſe this appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion
in me, (and queſtionleſs upon the ſame terms they will raiſe the ſame
in any other man) that Mr. <hi>Love</hi>'s confidence was not at leaſt as yet (I mean
in the entrance and beginning of his Speech) aſcended ſo high in his heart and
ſoul, as his tongue reported it unto the people. When <hi>Saul</hi> was dead, <hi>David</hi>
prayed no more for deliverance from him. And if <hi>Chriſt</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Love</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
confeſſeth) <hi>denied Prayer concerning his life,</hi> why might he not deny it
as concerning the <hi>quieting of his ſoul,</hi> and the <hi>bearing up of his heart againſt
the fear of Death?</hi> And if this be granted, evident it is that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Love</hi> did but
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, theatrically act the part of a Confident man upon the Scaffold.</p>
               <p>Several other things there are, which much dis-ſatisfie me touching the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimacy
and well-groundedneſs of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Love</hi>'s rejoycing and confidence at his
death, which I ſhall not at preſent (for brevities ſake) mention: How mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
ſtood between God and his Soul at his giving up of the Ghoſt, is a ſecret
too hard for my ſoul to enter into. I had rather hope (as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Aſh</hi> ſaid
unto him) that he made a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> end: nor do I deſire to leave any touch
or tincture of a contrary impreſſion in any man; My whole intent in what
hath been ſaid hitherto, is to put that confidence to rebuke which he brought
with him to the Scaffold, not to prove that he died in unbelief.</p>
               <p>Concerning that vain-glorious and light Conceit, That his Death ſhould turn
to ſuch an high Account of Honor unto him, becauſe <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi>
glorified God by the ſame death, and becauſe he read of <hi>Saints</hi> to be <hi>behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall ſpeak little to it, ſuppoſing that it weighs no more then the duſt
of the Ballance in the Judgement of any conſidering man. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Love</hi> well knew,
that it is not <hi>poena,</hi> but <hi>cauſa, quae facit Martyrem,</hi> not the puniſhment (much
leſs the kinde of puniſhment) that makes a Martyr; Which makes me a little to
marvel with what face he could ſay (as afterwards we ſhall hear him ſaying)
<hi>That whatſoever men may judge, yet he died a Martyr. Iohn Baptiſt</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed,
not ſimply for his Conſcience, or for the diſcharge of his Conſcience,
but for the diſcharge of his Conſcience, being honeſt and good, and rightly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed:
Whereas M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Love</hi> ſuffered a beheading, if for the diſcharge of his
Conſcience (which I think to conſidering men muſt needs be very queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able)
yet was it for the diſcharge of an erroneous conſcience (as his Petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
themſelves pleaded by way of extenuation of his Crime) yea, indeed of a
conſcience ſo deſperate erroneous and corrupt, that the like conſcience hath
ſcarce been heard of, no not among the Heathen themſelves (much leſs among
Chriſtians) <hi>viz.</hi> That a man ſtands bound, in ſtead of being ſubject to the
Powers that are (which is the expreſs Commandment of God) to deſtroy or
practice the deſtruction of theſe Powers: So that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Love</hi>'s conſcience for
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115116:20"/>
which (as he ſaith) he ſuffered, being truly interpreted, was ſuch a conſcience
by which he judged himſelf bound to act in a Diametral oppoſition to the
plain and expreſs revealed Will of God; And whether ſuch a conſcience as
this be a Chriſtian foundation of Martyrdom, let M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Love</hi>'s greateſt Friends
judge. Concerning <hi>Paul</hi> and the Saints ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> they were
<hi>beheaded for the Word of God, and for the teſtimony of Ieſus;</hi> Whereas M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Love</hi>
(as himſelf acknowledged in his <hi>Narrative</hi> written with his own hand, and
delivered unto the Parliament) was to ſuffer beheading (in caſe he ſhould not
obtain pardon from them) <hi>for his ſundry and great Offences;</hi> confeſſing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,
that <hi>by what he had done, he was an object of their juſt displeaſure:</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,
<hi>that by their juſtice they might in one day leave a Flock without a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd
a Wife without an Husband, Children without a Father, &amp;c.</hi> Doubtleſs
neither <hi>Paul</hi> nor the <hi>Saints</hi> mentioned by <hi>M. Love,</hi> were objects of the juſt
diſpleaſure of thoſe who beheaded them; nor were they beheaded for their
ſundry and great Offences, nor yet by the juſtice of thoſe who puniſhed them
with death. Therefore <hi>M. Love</hi> being partaker with <hi>Iudas</hi> in his ſin, the cauſe
of his death, can reap no honor for having <hi>Iohn</hi> or <hi>Paul,</hi> or the Saints his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions
in the kinde of his death: And indeed, might he not as well (yea and
much better, all this duly conſidered) have propheſied of ſhame and diſhonor
likely to acrue unto him by ſuch a kinde of death, which had been frequently
inflicted upon <hi>Papiſts, Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Ieſuits</hi> for treaſonable practices againſt the
State and Supream Rulers thereof, as indulge himſelf with a conceit, That his
death muſt needs become a Crown of Honor unto him, becauſe <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi>
and the great Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> died the ſame kinde of death, though (as the
world knoweth) upon far different occaſions?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 2.</head>
               <p>In this Section Mr. <hi>Love</hi> buſieth himſelf in waſhing a Blackamoor, hoping
by that time he hath done, to make him as white as Snow: That he <hi>ſuffereth for
the Word, and Conſcience, and not for medling in State-matters;</hi> he proves,
1. Becauſe it is an old guiſe of the Devil, to impute the cauſe of Gods Peoples
Sufferings, to be Contrivements againſt the State. 2. Becauſe the Rulers of
<hi>Iſrael</hi> would have put <hi>Jeremy</hi> to death upon a Civil account, whereas the true
ground was the truth of his Propheſie, and that this made them angry with
him. 3. Becauſe <hi>Paul,</hi> though he did but preach Chriſt, yet the people would
have him dye, under a pretence that he a was mover of Sedition. 4. (And
laſtly) becauſe himſelf ſaith, That his Life is pretended to be taken away upon
a Civil account, whereas it is indeed, becauſe he purſueth his Covenant, will
not proſtitute his Principles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Light and darkneſs have (in a maner) as much
communion between them, as the three firſt of theſe Arguments with his
Cauſe; For, is any guiſe of the Devil whatſoever, a Demonſtration or proof
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115116:20"/>
of Mr. <hi>Loves</hi> Innocency, or that he muſt needs ſuffer for the Word and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
and not for Statizing out of his Sphaer? Who is able to finde out the
Quadrature of this Circle? Or muſt Mr. <hi>Love</hi> needs be innocent of the Crimes
charged upon him, and proved againſt him; becauſe <hi>Ieremy</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent
from thoſe Imputations, which without any proof at all were charged
upon them? Or muſt thoſe Magiſtrates, who, being perſons of known godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
and worth (at leaſt a great part of them) yea, and Mr. <hi>Loves</hi> real and
cordial Friends (moſt of them) upon Tryal found Mr. <hi>Love</hi> guilty, and paſſed
Sentence upon him accordingly; muſt theſe (I ſay) of neceſſity be Corrupt,
Malicious, Enemies to the Truth and Word of God, becauſe the Rulers of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> with whom <hi>Ieremy</hi> had to do, and the people with whom <hi>Paul</hi> had
to do, were of no better Principles or Temper? Certainly, neither Satan, nor
<hi>Ieremy,</hi> nor <hi>Paul,</hi> nor their Adverſaries, are any Legal or Rational Compur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gators
for Mr. <hi>Love</hi> in his Cauſe now in Agitation: Indeed if he, or any Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate
for him, could as ſubſtantially prove, as he confidently aſſerts, that
which follows in the fourth place, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>his life was pretended</hi> (I ſuppoſe
he would rather have ſaid, <hi>intended,</hi> though neither would be very proper) <hi>to
be taken away becauſe he purſues his Covenant, and will not proſtitute his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
to the ambition and luſts of men,</hi> this would amount ſomewhat near
to a Proof of his Concluſion: But alas! for him to affirm ſuch things as theſe,
not onely without any ſufficient, yea, or tolerable proof, or colour of proof,
but even againſt his own Conceſſions and Confeſſions (in his Narrative ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
under the former Section, wherein he pretends over and over to Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity)
proves nothing elſe, but that either he wanteth ingenuity, or the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
of his own heart, or both; when he ſpake (§. 4.) thus, <hi>God is my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord,
whom I ſerve in the Spirit, I speak the truth, I lye not, I do not bring a
revengeful heart to the Scaffold this day,</hi> &amp;c. I marvel what the man means by
a <hi>revengeful Heart, Rancor, bitterneſs of Spirit, Animoſity, &amp;c.</hi> Surely he is
a <hi>Barbarian</hi> unto me, and ſpeaks a Language which I underſtand not: To
charge Ingenuous and Conſcientious men with <hi>taking away his life becauſe he
purſues his Covenant, will not proſtitute his Principles and Conſcience to the
ambition and luſts of men</hi> (with much more of like ſtrain, of which afterwards)
is in my underſtanding, as pregnant as expreſs a Symptome of a <hi>revengeful
Heart, Rancor,</hi> &amp;c. as a perſon in his condition is lightly capable of. Can
(ſaith <hi>Bildad</hi> in <hi>Iob) the Ruſh grow without mire?</hi> Or is it poſſible that ſuch
virulency and viperouſneſs of words as thoſe, ſhould proceed from any other
Principle, but from an heightned ſpirit of Rancor, Bitterneſs and Revenge?
But what Article in <hi>Mr. Loves</hi> Covenant was it, for his purſuit whereof his
Life was taken from him? Is there, was there any ſuch Article in this Covenant,
by which he ſtood in conſcience bound to trinket with the declared and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115116:21"/>
Enemies of the State and Nation, to attempt the undermining or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbing
of the preſent Government here, by Correſpondencies and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication
of Councels with Forreign States? Or was it for any thing elſe, but
ſuch accurſed Practices as theſe, and that proved againſt him by many witneſſes,
yea, and confeſſed in his Narrative by himſelf, that his Life was taken from
him? When I compare thoſe Paſſages in his Narrative (which he would it
ſeems have looked upon as a Maſterpiece of Ingenuity) wherein he owns the
<hi>Iuſtice of the Parliament,</hi> confeſſeth himſelf an <hi>Object of their juſt displeaſure,</hi>
craves <hi>pardon for his ſundry and great Offences,</hi> &amp;c. with the words lately men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,
and many others of like ſtrain in the ſequel of this Speech, wherein
he juſtifieth himſelf in the higheſt, makes himſelf a Saint in what he had done;
a Martyr, in what he ſhould ſuffer, chargeth his Judges and the State with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting
him for the Word of God; his Conſcience, for not proſtituting his
Principles and Conſcience to their Ambition and Luſts (with ſeveral other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions
of a like Helliſh import) I cannot but ſtand amazed at the ſearedneſs
and debauchery of the Conſcience of the man, or how it ſhould ever enter
into his heart to think of being honorable in his death, who thus notoriouſly
and deſperately prevaricated with his own former ingenious Confeſſions at
the time of his death: Either let one or other of his Friends or Advocates
name what Principle it was, one or more; for the non-proſtitution whereof
to the ambition and luſts of men, he was adjudged to death, and make it good,
that it was for ſuch a non-proſtitution that he was thus adjudged; or elſe the
world ſhall have ground in abundance to believe That Mr. <hi>Love</hi> acted the part
of a moſt Unchriſtian Calumniator upon the Scaffold in the very approaches
of death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 3.</head>
               <p>Here we have the ſecond part of the Theatrical flaſhy flouriſhes of Mr.
<hi>Loves</hi> confidence: But ſtrange it is, that ſuch virulent and deſperate ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies
as he had breathed out from his ſoul in the words immediately pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding,
ſhould be ſeconded with ſuch confidential raptures and gloryings as
theſe. Is the exerciſing of revenge upon his enemies, the riſe and bottom of
Mr. <hi>Loves</hi> confidence in God? Doubtleſs Mr. <hi>Love</hi> here ſacrificed to an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known
God: But the copyhold of his confidence hath been touched already;
whereas he aſſumeth unto himſelf the honor of having been <hi>an Inſtrument in
the Church-Pulpit of bringing others to Heaven,</hi> it is well if he ſtretcheth not
himſelf beyond his line. Whether he hath brought any to Heaven, or no, I
know not, poſſibly it may ſo be: But certain I am, that of later times he hath
brought many to ſome Helliſh practiſes. The ſeveral happy changes which
here he promiſeth unto himſelf, I could with more liberty of Faith have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved
might be performed unto him, had he not ſo lately made that unhappy
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115116:21"/>
                  <hi>change</hi> of an humble Penitentiary and Confeſſor of his ſin, into an haughty
and ſtubborn juſtifier of himſelf, and calumniator of other men. How his
<hi>Speech upon the Scaffold ſhould bring glory to God</hi> in any other ſence, then that
wherein (in the Apoſtles phraſe) <hi>The lie</hi> of men <hi>aboundeth to his glory,</hi> I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
not. I hear that one who was preſent at it, openly ſaid, <hi>That there was
more Divinity in</hi> Canterburies <hi>death then his</hi> (or words to ſuch an effect;) and
that another having heard the ſaid Speech, brake out in theſe or the like
words: <hi>Lord have mercy upon us, what ſhall we ſay, or do, when men will</hi> (or
dare) <hi>tell lies at their death.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 4.</head>
               <p>In this Section we have a moſt worthy and Chriſtian Profeſſion, as far as
the intereſt of words can lightly contribute towards it. O that there had been
an heart in the Profeſſor to have given a <hi>real</hi> account of Truth in this his <hi>verbal</hi>
Profeſſion. But alaſs! The ſame Fountain, though not out of the ſame hole,
which ſends forth theſe ſweet Waters here, ſends forth moſt bitter Waters
elſewhere, as we have taſted in part, and may taſte further afterwards. Doth
Mr. <hi>Love</hi> think that either God or men, will judge ſuch a man to be <hi>free
from all rancor, all bitterneſs of ſpirit, a revengeful heart, that he hath forgiven
from his heart his worſt enemies, &amp;c.</hi> Who loveth all words that may do them
miſchief, who cuts them with his Tongue as with a ſharp Razor, who ſpits out
of his mouth the poyſon of Aſpes in their very Faces, and at the time of his
going out of the world, is more intent and bent in his ſpirit (as far as a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
eſtimate can be made) to leave them an inheritance of Hatred, Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny,
Trouble, and of all maner of miſchiefs, and evil intreaties from the
world, then upon any other deſign whatſoever? whereas he ſeems deſirous
to diſparage his Enemies (as he calls them) in compariſon of himſelf in this,
That though <hi>they denied mercy unto him,</hi> yet he had <hi>begged mercy for them;</hi>
and though <hi>they would not forgive him, yet he had forgiven them;</hi> the truth is,
That even this alſo is no better then a ſlander: For upon what ground could he
judg, That they had not as well <hi>begged mercy</hi> for him, as he for them? Or did
they therefore <hi>deny</hi> him <hi>mercy,</hi> or not <hi>forgive</hi> him, becauſe they executed the
Laws of God, with the execution whereof they were entruſted? I believe
they forgave him in ſuch a ſence as he forgave them; and if ſo, they forgave
him much more then he them. I preſume Mr. <hi>Love</hi> forgave them onely ſuch
debts as they had contracted by injuring him, not what they had contracted
by ſinning againſt God: If ſo, then all that Mr. <hi>Love</hi> forgave them, amounts
to nothing at all; and this by his own confeſſion (a little before) who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged
the Juſtice of their proceedings againſt him: Therefore if they
forgave him (as I preſume in charity they did) the debt which he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted
by injuring them, their forgiveneſs of him was much more Chriſtian
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115116:22"/>
and worthy then his of them. But the forgiveneſs of the debt which he had
contracted by ſinning againſt the Laws of God, the juſt Laws of the Land (ſo
acknowledged by himſelf) the peace of the Nation, the lives of other men,
by the non-execution of Juſtice, he had no reaſon to expect at their hands,
conſidering that they <hi>are the Miniſters of God to take vengeance on them that do
evil,</hi> Rom. 13. 4.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 5.</head>
               <p>If Mr. <hi>Love</hi> may be his own Judge, nothing capital was ſufficiently proved
againſt him: Allow him his own ſence of the words, <hi>capital</hi> and <hi>ſufficiently,</hi>
and poſſibly he may be innocent. But the High Court of Juſtice, though a
great part (I think I might ſay, the greateſt) of the Members of it, were very
real friends to him, and their hearts much ſet to have holpen him out of the
bryars, as far as Juſtice and a good Conſcience would give way, were not of
Mr. <hi>Loves</hi> minde touching his Innocency; yea Mr. <hi>Love</hi> in his Narrative was
not of the ſame minde (in this point) with himſelf here; How he came by ſo
much Innocency between the time of his exhibiting the ſaid Narrative to the
Parliament, and the time of his coming to the Scaffold, his beſt Advocate (I
ſuſpect) would be aſhamed to declare. Innocency is not contracted by obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy,
or by the greateſt confidence in denial of the Truth. Mr. <hi>Love</hi> when he
ingenuouſly (as himſelf profeſſed) acknowledged the Juſtice of the Parliament
in their proceedings againſt him, did plainly enough confeſs that the Proof a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
him, was not empty, but as high and full as the Charge it ſelf. Thoſe
Expreſſions, That no witneſs <hi>proved that ever he writ a Letter or directed any
man to write a Letter into</hi> Scotland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> plainly prove him to have been more
cautelous then chaſte: and that he walked all along with his fellows in their
unhallowed practices, under the protection of that Motto, <hi>Si non caſtè, tamen
cautè.</hi> He that deſires to know more particularly how Mr. <hi>Love</hi> with the reſt
of his fellow Trinketers, divided their thoughts and endeavors between doing
of miſchief on the one hand, and the keeping themſelves out of danger,
what miſchief ſoever they ſhould do on the other hand, may receive ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
onely by a peruſal of the ſix and ſeven pages of a ſmall Diſcourſe lately
publiſhed under the title of, <hi>A ſhort Plea for the Commonwealth;</hi> whereas he
affirmeth, That <hi>all that was ſworn againſt him, was,</hi> That <hi>he was preſent when
Letters were read, and that he made a motion to give Money to</hi> Maſſey, is a
moſt ſhameleſs and horrid untruth, as appears by the Depoſitions of ſeveral
Witneſſes againſt him. Captain <hi>Potter</hi> depoſed, That he carried the Letters
ſent from <hi>Bampfield,</hi> from <hi>Argile, Loudon, Lothian, Belcarris,</hi> and another
from a nameleſs perſon (ſuppoſed to be Mr. <hi>Baily)</hi> to Mr. <hi>Love</hi> to take ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
upon them. This Letter had the letter <hi>L</hi> endorſed upon it, whereupon
this Captain <hi>Potter</hi> conceived it to have been intended to Mr. <hi>Love,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115116:22"/>
carried it to him. This witneſs further depoſed, That Mr. <hi>Love</hi> himſelf
and Mr. <hi>Jaquel</hi> read thoſe Letters that were opened, and opened the others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
and read them likewiſe, and diſcourſed of them, and upon advice reſolved
to do nothing in it (the buſineſs negotiated in theſe Letters.) This is more then
that <hi>All,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Love</hi> affirmeth was ſworn againſt him. The ſame witneſs
yet further depoſed, That Mr. <hi>Love</hi> and Dr. <hi>Drake</hi> were appointed to draw
up a Letter to be ſent into <hi>Scotland</hi> to Col. <hi>Bampfield,</hi> and that this Letter
was left at his ſhop, and that he apprehended that it came from Mr. <hi>Love.</hi>
This is yet more then Mr. <hi>Loves All.</hi> Major <hi>Robert Huntington</hi> (another
witneſs) depoſed, That a Queſtion being moved about a Commiſſion to be
ſent into <hi>Holland</hi> to the Lord <hi>Willoughby</hi> of <hi>Parham,</hi> Col. <hi>Graves, Maſſey,</hi>
and others; what power they had to give or ſend ſuch a Commiſſion, Mr.
<hi>Drake</hi> anſwered, <hi>We have the Kings Command for it, and the Authority of
ſome ſecluded Parliament men, which I look upon as the Power beyond that now
ſitting:</hi> Whereupon Mr. <hi>Love</hi> replied, <hi>Come, come, let it go.</hi> This is not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
more, but much more (in import and weightineſs of crime) then what
Mr. <hi>Love</hi> affirmeth was ſworn againſt him. Inſtance might be given in ſundry
particulars beſides theſe depoſed upon Oath againſt him by other the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,
whereby Mr. <hi>Love</hi> may be evicted not to have been ſo conſciencious or
tender of ſpeaking nothing but Truth, as becomes a Miniſter of the Goſpel,
eſpecially at ſuch a time, when he is called immediately to give up an account of
his Stewardſhip to his great <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter,</hi> with whom there is no place
for any man that <hi>loveth and maketh a lye,</hi> Revel. 22. 15.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 6.</head>
               <p>We heard (§. 1.) that M. <hi>Love</hi> pleaſed himſelf much with his Conformity
to <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> in the kinde of his death (though he was conformable to <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi>
in the occaſion and cauſe of his death) here to make his face to ſhine like
the Sun in the eyes of weak and dim-ſighted men; he conforms himſelf to
<hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf in his Accuſers; although herein alſo he much forgets himſelf
in calling thoſe <hi>Chriſts</hi> Accuſers, whom the Evangeliſts call <hi>Witneſſes.</hi> What
he affirmeth that he may <hi>without vanity or falſhood</hi> ſay of his, whether wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
or accuſers, as far as my Informations, which I judge competent in the
caſe, do extend, he cannot affirm without both. I never heard of any diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement
between them in the leaſt about any thing relating to M. <hi>Love,</hi> much
leſs of any of them contradicting himſelf; Nor do I know any ſufficient
ground to believe that one of them ſhould in writing pray him to forgive him
the wrong he had done him, or that he told him any ſuch ſtory as he relates;
conſidering firſt that (§. 8.) he tells an untruth of the ſame kinde, as <hi>viz.</hi> that on
the night before his Execution, there was an <hi>inſulting</hi> Letter written unto him
to tell him, that after he was dead, there ſhould be ſomething publiſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115116:23"/>
him to his ſhame: The Letter he ſpeaks of, not having the leaſt touch
or ſavor of any inſultation, nor threatning any thing to be publiſhed to his
ſhame after his death, but was grave and ſober, full of love and reſpects to him,
as an unpartial peruſal of it will inform any man, (it being ſince printed by the
Author upon occaſion of ſuch an unchriſtian aſperſion caſt upon it by M. <hi>Love.</hi>
Secondly, that none of his Accuſers (as he terms them) or Witneſſes, did te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie
any thing againſt him, but what (as far as I underſtand) they ſtand by
and own to this hour; no nor any thing (to my beſt remembrance) that
makes more againſt him then his own Narrative and Confeſſions here. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
Becauſe what he immediately ſubjoyns (towards the cloſe of this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction)
I have reaſon in abundance to believe is abſolutely falſe; as <hi>viz.</hi> That
<hi>ſome of his Witneſſes were terrified, others hired, ſome fined before they would
teſtifie againſt him:</hi> For though a Fine was pronounced to be impoſed on one
of them, which after upon his conformity was omitted, yet it was not <hi>before
he would, i.e.</hi> was willing to <hi>teſtifie againſt</hi> him: For this he freely offered in
Court to do before his <hi>Fining:</hi> Nor was he <hi>fined</hi> for refuſing to teſtifie againſt
M. <hi>Love,</hi> being ready enough (as was ſaid) to do this without <hi>fining,</hi> but for
refuſing to take an Oath according to the Law juſtly provided in ſuch caſes.
But for him to affirm that any of his Witneſſes were either <hi>terrified,</hi> or <hi>hired,</hi>
in order to the drawing of any Teſtimony from them <hi>againſt</hi> him, was to
wrong his Conſcience at ſuch a time, when it moſt nearly concerned him to
have been moſt tender of it. He hath Friends and Favorers ſurviving in great
numbers, many of them men of learning and parts, and that know how to
inform themſelves, of any thing that is like to make for his Vindication; One
or more of theſe ſhall do the office of a friend to his Name and Memory, by
engaging themſelves to make due proof of what he here affirmeth, <hi>viz. That
ſome of his Witneſſes were terrified, others, &amp;c.</hi> that ſo the blot and ſhame of
a miſcarrying tongue may not teſt upon him. Fourthly, Becauſe by reaſon of
his ſwallowing even Camels of untruth ſo frequently and familiarly as he doth
in this Diſcourſe, I have ground to be jealous (at leaſt) leſt as the conſcience
of the <hi>Ieſuit</hi> is moulded into this principle, that it is lawful to ſay or do things
otherwiſe unlawful, <hi>in ordine ad bonum ſpirituale;</hi> ſo <hi>Mr. Love</hi>'s conſcience
ſtood free and large in him, to ſpeak and do almoſt any thing <hi>in ordine ad bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num
Presbyteriale.</hi> Fifthly (and laſtly) Becauſe <hi>M. Love</hi> was rooted to
the center of the Earth, and built up to the midſt of Heaven in ſuch a Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
in Divinity, which gives fair quarter to the fouleſt practices that are, in
the Saints eſpecially, when they certainly know they ſhall die preſently, <hi>viz.</hi>
that no perpetration of ſin and wickedneſs whatſoever, can ſeparate thoſe
from the love of God in Chriſt, who have at any time believed in him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:115116:23"/>
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 7.</head>
               <p>I never met with ſo many ſenceleſs and unſavory Contradictions within ſo
ſmall a compaſs, as in this Speech: How can Mr. <hi>Love</hi> ſay that <hi>he will
not judge his Judges, nor yet juſtifie them,</hi> when as in the words immediately
following, he muſt of neceſſity either do the one or the other: For, if he
ſuppoſeth the Oath, for the ſake whereof his Judges (as he ſaith) cut off his
head, to have been juſtifiable or lawful, and they by the tenor and band of this
Oath ſtood bound to do what they did in cutting off his Head, then he clearly
juſtifieth them; if he ſuppoſeth either the ſaid Oath to have been unlawful,
or their Fact in cutting off his Head to have been beſides, or contrary to this
Oath, and that they had no Ingagement upon them otherwiſe to do it, then he
<hi>judgeth</hi> them. But the truth is, we can upon no better or more favorable
account eaſe Mr. <hi>Love</hi> in the greateſt part of things uttered by him in this
Speech, then by conceiving that the words ſpoken by him, bear a far differing
ſence and ſignification in his underſtanding, from that which they bear in ours:
For, what is it to judge in our ſence of the Word, then to charge with Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
Unrighteouſneſs, acting contrary to the Word or Laws of God? And
whither Mr. <hi>Love</hi> doth not again and again, and ſeven times over (in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe)
thus charge his Judges, I refer to his Friends themſelves to judge and
determine: Therefore in the ordinary acception of the word, <hi>Judge,</hi> when
Mr. <hi>Love</hi> ſaith, he will <hi>not judge his Judges,</hi> he ſpeaks beſides the Truth: And
though here he refuſeth to <hi>juſtifie</hi> them, yet when the Spirit of Ingenuity was
upon him (as himſelf once and again profeſſeth it was, in the Compoſure of
his Narrative) he did fairly and fully juſtifie them, as we have already heard,
and is further manifeſt in the Narrative it ſelf Printed herewith. By the
way; of how ſad and bleeding a conſideration is it, that a man whoſe heart
ſerved him to be ingenuous in his life, ſhould quench ſo Chriſtian a Spirit, and
ſuffer himſelf to be hardened at the time of his death. Beſides, did he not
fully juſtifie his Judges in his laſt Petition to the Parliament, in theſe words: <hi>He
humbly acknowledgeth that he hath ſo highly violated the Laws of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,
as that thereby he hath rendred himſelf guilty of the Sentence of death
juſtly paſſed on him by the High Court of Juſtice?</hi> The words immediately pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding
theſe, are of a like import.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 8.</head>
               <p>I ſhall ſay little upon this Section, having already given notice how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truly
and unchriſtianly he calls the Letter here ſpecified, <hi>an inſulting Letter.</hi>
Yet to ſay, that it was written to him for ſuch an end as here he chargeth it
with, <hi>viz.</hi> To <hi>tell him that after he was dead ſomething ſhould be publiſhed againſt
him,</hi> &amp;c. as if this had been either the onely or the principal drift of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
is much more diſ-ingenuous. I preſume there is no man that ſhall pleaſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115116:24"/>
to read this Letter (being ſince printed) but will acknowledge the drift and
ſcope of it to have been honorable and <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and not unworthy the beſt
and deareſt Friend <hi>M. Love</hi> had.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9, 10, 11, 12" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 9, 10, 11, 12.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. Love</hi> here inſtanceth <hi>five Aſperſions laid upon him</hi> in point of practice.
As for thoſe of <hi>Extortion</hi> and <hi>Adultery,</hi> I never ſo much as heard <hi>M. Love,</hi> and
either of them, named together. I will not ſay that <hi>M. Love</hi> prudentially ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecteth
himſelf to ſuch aſperſions, from which he knows he can ſufficiently
purge himſelf. But he that lyeth under a ſuſpition of ſeveral Crimes, and is able
fully to aſſert his innocency in reſpect of any one or more of them, gains an
advantage hereby to make the purgation of himſelf from the reſt the more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditable.
Concerning <hi>Murther;</hi> neither did I ever hear this formally, or in
the letter of it, laid to his charge; But that in his Communications with the
King of Scots, and other perſons of his adherency, declared Enemies to the
State and Government of this Commonwealth, he was eminently and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendently
a <hi>murtherer,</hi> hath been ſufficiently proved againſt him upon oath, by
many witneſſes; yea his own Confeſſions in his Narrative and Petitions do not
fall much ſhort of ſuch a proof. Therefore whereas (§. 11.) he traduceth thoſe
who charge him with the <hi>guilt of that blood,</hi> which hath been ſpilt in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
Wars between the two Nations; that they do by him as <hi>Nero did by the
Chriſtians,</hi> &amp;c. (a notion ſuggeſted by the ſame ſpirit of Revenge unto his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<hi>Gibbons</hi> alſo) he deals by them as <hi>Potiphar</hi>'s wife did by her ſervant <hi>Joſeph,</hi>
who being incontinent her ſelf, accuſed him of incontinency to his Lord, becauſe
he refuſed to gratifie her luſt. <hi>M. Love, Mr. Gibbon,</hi> and the reſt of their Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation
being deſirous that this State, and thoſe in preſent power amongſt
us, ſhould condeſcend to their impolitique Principles and Humors, in admitting
the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> King to a <hi>monarchical</hi> Throne over this Nation, and herein to own
a <hi>Scotiſb</hi> Superintendency over them and the Nation; and they refuſing to
comport with them in ſuch their luſts and deſires, and attempting by the beſt,
and (indeed) the onely means they had to withſtand the ſaid King in his claim
to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Throne, together with the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Nation (his imperious and
proud Abettors in this his Claim) upon this Account, and this onely, <hi>Mr. Love</hi>
and <hi>M. Gibbon</hi> charge the Blood that hath been ſpilt in the preſent Wars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
the Nations, upon the State and preſent Powers amongſt us. Let the
world, if there be a part of it yet unbewitched and capable of judging, give
Sentence, in caſe there be blood ſpilt between a company of Thieves, and a
like party of harmleſs Travellers by the way, upon occaſion of an Aſſault made
by the former upon the latter, whether the ſpilling of this blood be to be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
upon the latter or the former. Nor let any Advocate either for <hi>M. Love</hi>
or <hi>M. Gibbon,</hi> think to juſtifie them in their imputation of the ſaid blood ſpilt,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115116:24"/>
upon the State or men in preſent power, by pretending that they ſent an Army
into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and made war upon the ſaid King and <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Nation, before
they attempted any thing againſt this: For evident it was, and is, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances
purporting hoſtility in that Nation againſt this, ſtanding as then they
did, that the warlike Preparations and Levies at this time on foot and haſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in that Nation, ſorely threatned and endangered this; So that the war ſince
breaking out between the two Nations, was not occaſioned (or properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun)
by the Engliſh Army ſent into <hi>Scotland,</hi> but by thoſe Levies and formid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
Preparations for War, which the Scotiſh King and Nation were advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
with an high hand, before the ſaid Engliſh Army came amongſt them:
Nor is there the leaſt colour or pretext of Reaſon to think, that in caſe the ſaid
Army had not entred the Scotiſh Territories, the War hereby might have
been prevented; becauſe the Scotiſh Nation was now big with this bloody
birth, ready to cry out and to be delivered, when the ſaid Army entred. All
that can reaſonably be imputed to the entrance of the Engliſh Army into <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi>
quarters before their entrance into Engliſh, is &amp; was, That <hi>Scotland</hi> by this
means became the Seat of the War, which otherwiſe <hi>England</hi> muſt have been.
It is the opinion and judgement of <hi>Civilians</hi> (generally) That <hi>men may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
make War when they fear, leſt themſelves ſhould be warred upon. We ought
not</hi> (ſaith <hi>Albericus Gentilis</hi> a learned Civilian in <hi>Oxford</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s
days, <hi>we ought not) to expect preſent Force: it is more ſafe if we meet with that
which is future;</hi> with much more to this purpoſe tranſcribed by M. <hi>Prynne</hi> in
his third Part of the <hi>Soveraign Power of Parliaments and Kingdoms,</hi> cap. 14.
where a judicious Reader may receive plenary ſatisfaction, not ſimply concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Lawfulneſs, but alſo the Neceſſity of the Parliaments ſending an Army
into <hi>Scotland,</hi> under ſuch circumſtances as then ruled. So that it was unworthineſs
of ſpleen and revenge both in M. <hi>Love</hi> and M. <hi>Gibbons</hi> (though they be both
great pretenders to meekneſs and clearneſs of ſpirit towards their Adverſaries)
not goodneſs of Conſcience that prompted them upon the Scaffold with this
imputation againſt thoſe whom they call their Adverſaries, <hi>viz.</hi> That they are
the men upon whoſe heads the blood ſpilt between the two Nations reſteth.
And as the high Prieſt with the chief Prieſts took it very hainouſly at the hand
of the Apoſtles, that they ſhould charge them with the crucifying of <hi>Chriſt;
(Ye have filled</hi> Jeruſalem, ſay they, <hi>with your Doctrine, and intend to bring this
mans blood upon us:)</hi> So do M. <hi>Love</hi> and his fellows ſwell with indignation
againſt thoſe, who entitle them to the late blood-ſhed between the Nations,
though their title in this kinde be as unqueſtionable, as that of the Prieſts to
the crucifying of Chriſt. It cannot upon any tolerable account of Reaſon be
ſaid, That had not the Engliſh Army entred <hi>Scotland,</hi> no blood between the
Nations had been ſpilt: but it may upon a very lively and pregnant account
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115116:25"/>
be ſaid, That had not M. <hi>Love,</hi> M. <hi>Gibbons,</hi> with the reſt of the Conſpiracy
tampered the King of Scots into an Agreement with that Nation by ſolemn
promiſſory engagement of themſelves and their Party in <hi>England,</hi> to ſtand by
him upon that condition, and by ſignifying unto him and his Party their diſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections
to the preſent Government, this blood had not been ſhed. And this
I have credibly heard to be the acknowledged ſoul-perſwaſion of one of the
greateſt and ableſt parts amongſt the Conſpirators. The Concluſion here is,
That both M. <hi>Love</hi> and M. <hi>Gibbon</hi> waſh their hands from blood with very
foul water, and which defiles them yet more, when they burthen their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries
(ſo called by them) with that guilt which ſticks ſo faſt and cloſe unto
themſelves, and is the fruit, not of the <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>Luſts</hi> of their Adverſaries,
but of their own.</p>
               <p>Whereas in purging himſelf from the Aſperſion of Lying, he ſaith thus, <hi>I
hope you will believe a dying man, who dare not look God in the face with a lie in
his mouth,</hi> intimating, as if his being ready to die, was a bridle in his lips to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain
him from lying; the truth is, according to that principle of his (former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
mentioned) that he, who ever once truly believed, can never by any ſin or
wickedneſs whatſoever loſe the love and favor of God; his being ready to die in
conjunction with a perſwaſion of his Saintſhip, ſhould rather be a temptation
upon him to lie or commit any other wickedneſs, then an engagement upon him
to refrain lying: For in caſe he were in hope of living ſtill in the world, and
ſhould practice lying or any other ſin, he had cauſe to fear, that though God
would not caſt him out of his ſaving Love for ſuch practices, yet he might, and
would ſeverely puniſh him otherwiſe. But when a perſon of ſuch a principle
certainly knows that he ſhall preſently die, he hath no ground to fear any pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
at all from God, for whatſoever he ſhall now either ſay or do, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
death (according to the ſaid principle) delivers him for ever out of his
hand. Nor am I free from all Jealouſie, but that the Principle I ſpeak of had
ſome malignant inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uence upon M. <hi>Love</hi>'s ſpirit, in many of thoſe unworthy
ſtrains and miſdemeanors which proceeded from him at his death. Whereas
he pleads to that particular indictment of lying, inſiſted upon by himſelf, That
<hi>what he denied before the High Court of Juſtice, he neither afterwards confeſſed
himſelf, nor was it proved by others againſt him;</hi> very poſſibly, in his equivocal
ſence of the words, <hi>denying, proving</hi> and <hi>confeſſing,</hi> that which he pleads may
be true: But M. <hi>Love,</hi> had he been ingenuous when he was before a Court of
Judicature, where the common and known Dialect of the Law uſeth to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
and where critical and captious Formalities of ſpeech are not expected, he
ſhould have denied onely ſuch things, which according to a Law-ſenſe of the
words uſed by him, he could truly have denied. Upon theſe terms he could
neither have denied that he ever wrote Letter to the King, Queen, Church
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115116:25"/>
or State of <hi>Scotland;</hi> nor yet that he never received any Letter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Becauſe
in the Law-ſignification of the words, <hi>writing Letters,</hi> they are as well ſaid
to write Letters, who are either adviſing or conſenting to, or directing in the
writing of them, as they who write them with a Pen: And I preſume, That if
any man aſperſed Mr. <hi>Love</hi> with the Crime of Lying, in this particular, by <hi>ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
they meant equivocating, and ſo uſed the milder term of the two in their
Charge. But whereas he preſently ſaith, That <hi>he came</hi> [meaning to die upon
the Scaffold] <hi>onely for moving for money for</hi> Maſſey, <hi>and for being preſent when
Letters were read, &amp;c.</hi> How notorious an untruth this is, hath been already
ſhewed; where we found Matters of a far higher Nature proved againſt him
then theſe: But I cannot but tremble to meet with thoſe words from his
mouth, <hi>That for the things I am condemned, neither doth God, nor my own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
condemn me;</hi> When I compare them with words coming from himſelf,
both in his Narrative and Petition a few days before; In his Narrative (as was
formerly obſerved) he acknowledged once and again the Juſtice of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
in their Proceedings againſt him: In his Third Petition, he profeſſeth
himſelf <hi>unfeignedly ſorrowful for his violating the Laws of this Commonwealth:</hi>
In his Fourth and laſt, he hath theſe words, <hi>The conſideration whereof</hi> [ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of the Grace of the Parliament in his Reprieval] <hi>melteth the heart of your
Petitioner, and maketh him, after a more narrow ſearch into his heart and ways,
more deeply ſenſible then ever of his ſin againſt God, and more ſorrowful for his
High Crimes and Offences againſt the Parliament in his late and great miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages,
&amp;c.</hi> Doth not God condemn ſin committed againſt him, as well in Mr.
<hi>Love,</hi> as in other men? Or was Mr. <hi>Love Antinomianized</hi> at his death, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
that God ſeeth no ſin in believers? Or however, was Mr. <hi>Loves</hi> Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
ſo deſperately now hardned, as not to <hi>condemn him for high Crimes, and
great Miſcarriages?</hi> If his meaning were, That God had pardoned the ſins
for which he was brought to the Scaffold, and in this reſpect did not <hi>condemn</hi>
him for them; or that his Conſcience, notwithſtanding theſe <hi>ſins,</hi> did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn
him for an Hypocrite, <hi>nulli fidian,</hi> or the like, the words were nothing
but a meer deluſion of the people.</p>
               <p>When he comes to waſh off the aſperſion of his being a man of a <hi>turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
ſpirit,</hi> (§ 12.) How notoriouſly (and indeed ſenſleſly) doth he prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
with his Cauſe in hand, doing like a man that ſhould with an importune
confidence aſſert his Chaſtity; and yet immediately commit the crime of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery
in the very face of thoſe, before whom he had endeavored ſuch a
Vindication of himſelf? For who is a man of a <hi>turbulent ſpirit,</hi> but he that
ſeeks and ſets himſelf to divide between Rulers, and thoſe that ought to live in
ſubjection unto them, by alienating the mindes and affections of the one from
the other: Upon which, there muſt needs follow an interruption and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115116:26"/>
of the Political Harmony and Accord in the State and Commonwealth?
Or what courſe can be taken by any man of a moſt deſperate Conſequence,
for the firing of the ſpirits of People, with Hatred and Revenge againſt
their Governors, then to accuſe them of Uſurpation of their Power on the
one hand, and with the Adminiſtration of it with Injuſtice and Cruelty on the
other; and withal to labor to poſſeſs the people with a conceit, That God
hath determined to caſt them out of the poſſeſſion of their Power with Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny
and Shame? Or are not theſe words of Mr. <hi>Loves, Thoſe who have
gotten power into their hands by policy, &amp;c.</hi> Words of this import, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
of as <hi>turbulent</hi> an inſpiration, as a <hi>tongue ſet on fire of Hell</hi> (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
ſpeaketh) could lightly utter? Is this Mr. <hi>Loves ingenuity,</hi> his <hi>meekneſs,</hi>
his <hi>ſweetneſs of ſpirit,</hi> his <hi>forgiving from his heart the worſt of his enemies?</hi> If
this be his <hi>forgiveneſs,</hi> what would his <hi>revenge</hi> have been? How true is that
intelligence which we have from <hi>Solomon, The tender mercies of the wicked are
cruel?</hi> Whereas the <hi>Cruelties</hi> (ſo called by Mr. <hi>Love)</hi> of juſt men, are <hi>tender
mercies.</hi> Neither can the perſons whom he ſo unchriſtianly traduceth, by any
act whatſoever, expreſs more Mercy, greater Compaſſion towards the many
Millions of perſons in the Land, then by cutting off evil doers from it by the
Sword of Juſtice, ſuch eſpecially who defile it with Blood. But with what
face could Mr. <hi>Love</hi> charge thoſe in Power, to have <hi>gotten</hi> this <hi>power into their
hand by policy;</hi> if by <hi>policy</hi> he means any thing diſhoneſt or diſhonorable unto
them? Were not thoſe, who now ſit in Parliament, lawfully called to theſe
places of truſt by the people? Or was it any ways diſhoneſt, or diſhonorable
in them, to keep their Covenant in bringing the Grand Delinquent and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiary
of the Land to <hi>condign puniſhment?</hi> Or to diſſolve that Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
under the intolerable Oppreſſions and Vexations whereof the
people of the Nation had now groaned theſe 500 years and upwards; wanting
either the heart or opportunity until now, to break the yoke of ſo cruel a
bondage? Or was it any <hi>policy</hi> in them, but what was moſt worthy men in
thoſe high places of truſt, committed unto them by the people; when they
clearly, and by ſufficient experience found, That the Houſe of Peers
who had no Parliamentary Intereſt granted unto them by the people, together
with ſome of their own Members, daily prevaricating with the common
cauſe, and real Intereſt of the people, palpably bent in their Counſels and Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
to have kept the Nation under the abomination of that Tyrannical Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency
and Power, from which it was now in an hopeful way of deliverance:
Was it (I ſay) any unworthy policy in thoſe now in power, to provide for
the Liberties, Peace and Safety of the people, by diſcharging the one and the
other from thoſe places of Intereſt and Power, which gave them the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity
of practiſing with ſo high an hand againſt them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:115116:26"/>
Whereas they are charged to <hi>uſe their Power with cruelty,</hi> this is ſo broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac'd
a calumny, that nothing need be ſaid for their vindication from it: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates
are not therefore <hi>cruel,</hi> becauſe they <hi>carry not the ſword in vain,</hi> or
becauſe, being <hi>Miniſters of God to take vengeance on evil doers,</hi> they <hi>fulfil
their Miniſtery</hi> in this kinde: Cruelty would be much more truly and juſtly
chargeable upon them, in caſe they ſhould carry the ſword in vain, and ſuffer
<hi>evil doers,</hi> Traytors, Incendiaries, Diſturbers of States and Commonwealths,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> to paſs unpuniſhed: And therefore, unleſs Mr. <hi>Love</hi> could either have produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
ſome better ground for his charge of <hi>Cruelty</hi> againſt the State then his own
ſufferings, or elſe have evicted, not onely the many evidences brought againſt
him as an <hi>evil doer,</hi> but his own confeſſions alſo in this behalf, he had provided
much better for his honor and conſcience too, by leaving this charge to be levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by ſome ſon of <hi>Belial,</hi> who hath neither honor nor conſcience to pollute.</p>
               <p>Whereas he undertakes to Propheſie, That thoſe in Power <hi>will loſe it with
Ignominy;</hi> it is well for them, that <hi>as the wrath of man worketh not the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs
of God,</hi> ſo neither doth the righteouſneſs of God accompliſh the wrath
of man: But upon what account doth Mr. <hi>Love</hi> propheſie this hard predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
againſt the State? If God revealed it unto him, certainly it is a <hi>new
light,</hi> and himſelf in the ſequel of this Speech chargeth us to take heed of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving
<hi>new Lights;</hi> it may be becauſe himſelf had no more, whither wiſdom
orgrace, then to loſe his Miniſtery <hi>with Ignominy,</hi> therefore meaſuring thoſe <hi>in
Power</hi> by himſelf, he conceived that neither would they have any more, then
to loſe their <hi>Miniſtery</hi> alſo upon the ſame terms: But I truſt, the perſons
whom he ignominiouſly deſtroys with his propheſie, will by wiſdom and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs
deſtroy the credit of his propheſie, and preſerve themſelves in Power
with Honor whileſt they live, and leave it with honor to their Succeſſors at their
death: It is moſt like that Mr. <hi>Love</hi> adventured his Reputation on this prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,
upon a confidence, That his Reputation amongſt unworthy perſons was
ſuch, that rather then they would ſuffer him, though dead, to lie under the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace
of a falſe Prophet, themſelves would make him a true, by tracing his
ſteps in ſeeking to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt them with Ignominy of their Power. The ſeed which
he had ſown, both f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>merly in his life, and now at his death, he conceived was
too ſpirituous and pregnant to rot under the clod, and that therefore he might be
bold to propheſie the ſpringing up of it after his death.</p>
               <p>He doth much more prudently, in referring himſelf to his <hi>Congregational
and Domeſtical Relations,</hi> to have it decided by theſe, whether he was <hi>a man of a
turbulent ſpirit</hi> or no: It is very probable that where he might rule the roſt, and
umpire in chief, he might be compoſed and calm enough: <hi>Doth the wilde aſs
bray</hi> (ſaith <hi>Job) when he hath graſs? or loweth the ox over his fodder?</hi> I believe,
that had the State judg'd it meet to be as condeſcentious to his humors and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115116:27"/>
as it is likely the <hi>Relations</hi> he ſpeaks of were, they ſhould not have taſted
much turbulency of ſpirit in him, at leaſt againſt themſelves: If he were alive,
I would calmly put this Queſtion to him, Whither <hi>the grief of his heart,</hi> which
he expreſſeth <hi>for the diviſion amongst Gods people,</hi> was occaſioned ſimply by the
<hi>Diviſion</hi> he ſpeaks of, and not rather from hence, That all the Godly in the land
would not ſo far reverence his judgement, as to conform &amp; ſubmit to it; I know
no man, <hi>the deſire of whoſe ſoul is not for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion amongst the Godly,</hi> upon ſuch
terms. I do in part believe him, <hi>That his judgement put him upon endeavors af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
all honorable and juſt ways for peace and love among the Godly;</hi> but I believe
withal, That his Ambition and height of ſpirit <hi>put him upon</hi> many <hi>ways</hi> alſo in
this kinde unjuſt and diſhonorable. His <hi>Principle</hi> (as he calls it) which teacheth
him to declare againſt <hi>ingaging to the preſent Power,</hi> and to term this <hi>A Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination,
rather then a Gospel-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> was affronted by a contrary <hi>Principle</hi> in
him a few days before; as, <hi>viz.</hi> when (in his ſecond Petition to the Parliament)
he ingageth himſelf <hi>to preſerve the civil peace and welfare of the Commonwealth,</hi>
and <hi>neither to plot, contrive or deſign any thing to the hurt of this preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi>
A like ingagement (and almoſt in the very ſame words) he maketh the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
time in his third Petition. In his laſt Petition, he declareth it as his <hi>full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution,
That he will neither Plot, Contrive, or Deſign any thing prejudicial to
the preſent Government, but will in his place and calling oppoſe any deſigns what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,
whether in this or the Neighbor Nation, that may tend to the ruine of
this Commonwealth.</hi> Doubtleſs, in theſe promiſes and ingagements (eſpecially
in the laſt) there is every whit as much comprehended, as can with reaſon be
imagined to be contained or intended in that <hi>Engagement to the State,</hi> at which
his Principle is ſo much offended; ſo that it is a plain caſe, that Mr. <hi>Love</hi> was
as unſtable as water in his Principles, and could at pleaſure <hi>proſtitute</hi> them,
though <hi>not to the ambition or luſts</hi> of other <hi>men,</hi> yet to his own: His <hi>fear of
Atheiſm and Popery coming into</hi> England, would be much more reaſonable then
yet it is, in caſe his Deſign of bringing in the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> King to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Throne
ſhould proſper, it being much more likely that he would <hi>give his power to the
Beaſt,</hi> as his Father, and many of his Predeceſſors had d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e before him, then
that thoſe in preſent Power ſhould do it: I ſhall not ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ge Mr. <hi>Love</hi> himſelf
with <hi>Atheiſm;</hi> but thoſe words ſpoken by him to the Sheriff, the occaſion
conſidered, <hi>Sir, I ſhall look God in the Face with what I ſay,</hi> have no enmity at
all in them againſt that horrid impiety.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 13.</head>
               <p>In this Section M. <hi>Love</hi> begins the account of his Principles: Where firſt
he pretends to <hi>bleſs God</hi> for that, which is notoriouſly untrue (unleſs he ſpeaks
Parables in plain words, and hath a meaning which I know not of) <hi>viz.</hi> That
<hi>neither an High Court, nor a Bloody Scaffold, hath made him in the leaſt to alter
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115116:27"/>
his Principles.</hi> His <hi>Principles</hi> now upon the Scaffold differ <hi>toto coelo,</hi> from
what they were a few days before, unleſs he then owned Principles that were
not his own (as we lately ſhewed from his own words in his Petitionary Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications
to the Parliament.) And what ſhould alter them, but the <hi>Scaffold</hi>
he ſpeaks of, is above my Reach or Reaſon to conceive. If his meaning be,
That his Principles are now, and formerly, the ſame <hi>Geometrically, i. e.</hi> Alike
proportioned to his reſpective Conditions, now, and then; ſo that as then they
were prudentially fitted to the exigence of his Condition, as then it ſtood, and
are now fitted with alike Prudence (as he conceived) to his Condition as now
it ſtandeth (in a far different poſture) I can believe him; But I do not believe
that he had any deſire to be underſtood in this ſence by his Auditory, when he
ſaith, <hi>That he ſtill retains as vehement a deteſtation of a Malignant Intereſt as
ever:</hi> Doubtleſs he doth not <hi>retain</hi> the ſame notion of <hi>Malignancy.</hi> The
word is now of a more contracted ſignification with him, then formerly.
Heretofore they were all <hi>Malignants,</hi> who aſſiſted the King againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament;
Now, not all they, nor ſcarce the one half of thoſe who aſſiſt him,
are ſuch; but onely they that come to his aſſiſtance, not having on a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian
Garment. If he had lived until now, he need not have put in a proviſo
to ſave in his Covenanting Brethren in <hi>Scotland</hi> harmleſs, from the ſuſpition of
Maglinancy for aſſiſting their King: For, whether it be the coming of their
wiſdom unto them, or the return of their Conſcience, they have quitted his
Aſſiſtance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 14.</head>
               <p>Here he talks of a <hi>regulated Monarchy,</hi> and a <hi>mixt Monarchy.</hi> There is
little leſs then <hi>contradictio in adjuncto,</hi> in both expreſſions. Law-makers (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs)
in Monarchical States, have ſometimes done their good wills to regulate
Monarchy by Laws: <hi>Sed vetuere patres, quod non potuere vetare.
Monarchies</hi> of the beſt Regulation by Laws, were yet as exorbitant in the
Practique, and in the exerciſe of Monarchical power, as if they had been Rule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
and Lawleſs. A <hi>mixt Monarchy</hi> (in ſtrictneſs of Speech) is as unproper as
a <hi>compounded ſimple.</hi> But Mr. <hi>Loves</hi> judgement concerning the preheminency
of a <hi>mixt Monarchy</hi> amongſt Governments, is not of ſo much weight, as to
counterpoiſe the lighteſt Argument <hi>in oppoſitum.</hi> His affection of <hi>hatred</hi> equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
bent againſt <hi>Court Paraſites, who would ſcrew up Monarchy into Tyranny,</hi>
and againſt <hi>thoſe who pull it down to bring in Anarchy,</hi> is praiſe-worthy; One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
I ſuſpect (in the latter Clauſe) an evil eye of inſinuation againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
as if he deſired to infuſe this fooliſh Faith into the people, That they
<hi>pulled down Monarchy,</hi> not with any intent to ſet up a better Government in
the ſtead of it, but <hi>to bring</hi> in Anarchy or Confuſion. Whether he was at any
time formerly <hi>for putting the King to death,</hi> or no, I cannot poſitively ſay;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115116:28"/>
if he was not, he was an unhappy man to expreſs himſelf, both in words and
deeds, ſo like unto a man of ſuch intentions as he did. He confeſſeth <hi>his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
formerly was, and ſtill is, for the bringing of Malignants, who did ſeduce him,
and drew him from the Parliament, to condign puniſhment.</hi> But what if <hi>Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants
did</hi> not ſo much <hi>ſeduce him</hi> in this kinde, as he them? who now deſerve,
and this according to the expreſs letter of the Covenant, to be <hi>brought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dign
puniſhment?</hi> They that beſt knew him, have often ſaid, That himſelf was
the head, and not the tayl, of thoſe Councels, by which he acted againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.
I know no alteration in the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> between what is now, and what
it was at the time Mr. <hi>Love</hi> ſpeaks of, unleſs it be in this; That the Parliament
now, both with more Chriſtianity and better Policy, cauſeth the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian
Intereſt to contain it ſelf in its own proper Channel, which before
was like the <hi>River</hi> Jordan <hi>in the time of Harveſt, when he overflows his
banks.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 15.</head>
               <p>Here M. <hi>Love</hi> profeſſeth that he dies <hi>with his judgement not ſatisfied to take
the Engagement,</hi> and yet <hi>prays God to forgive thoſe who ſubſcribe it:</hi> What is
this, being interpreted, but to pray to God to forgive thoſe concerning whom
he is <hi>not ſatisfied in his judgement,</hi> whether they ſin or no? But as <hi>Paul,</hi> having
firſt given this teſtimony to the <hi>Galatians, ye did run well,</hi> then expoſtulatingly
demands of them, <hi>who hindred you that you ſhould not obey (i. e.</hi> continue to
obey) <hi>the truth?</hi> So let me firſt give this Teſtimony to M. <hi>Love,</hi> (as I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
it already, being furniſhed with it from his own Petitions) He did ſome
few days before, <hi>run well,</hi> not ſimply in owning the preſent Government, but
alſo in engaging himſelf home to it, and for it: and then expoſtulate with his
friends (himſelf not being in a capacity to anſwer) <hi>who hindred him</hi> that he
ſhould not hold out in ſo good and commendable a race unto the end? He la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors
in the very fire to purge himſelf from the Crime (as now the Scaffold it
ſeems had made it) of his late owning the preſent Government; but the fire he
uſeth is purely elementary, and will not purge or burn: For if <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhai</hi>
gave the Title of King to <hi>Abſolom,</hi> there is little queſtion but in a ſenſe, and
that intended by them, it did of right belong to him; Neither the one nor the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of them gave the title of King to him, until he was proclaimed King by the
men of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yea and was poſſeſſed of the royal city <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> &amp; the Throne;
So that he was truly and properly King when the Title of King was given by
theſe men unto him; though it is true, he came to be a King, and ſo to have right
to ſuch a Title, in a moſt wicked and treaſonable way. So that both <hi>David</hi>
and <hi>Huſhai</hi> look'd upon <hi>Abſolom</hi> as a true King, though with uſurpation, when
they gave the Title unto him; and conſequently did nothing contrary to their
judgements and conſciences herein. But M. <hi>Love</hi> it ſeems was not perſwaded in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115116:28"/>
his judgement or conſcience, that the Parliament was the Parliament or Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream
Authority of the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> when he gave theſe Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles
unto them, therefore he ſinned againſt his conſcience in ſo doing: So that
ſaying, That herein <hi>he did not wrong or croſs his Principles,</hi> doth he not
plainly imply that his Principles and Conſcience thwart and croſs the one the
other? If he had any ſuch Principle, which either led him or gave him leave
to act or ſpeak againſt his Conſcience, it was a Principle of darkneſs and of
death. If <hi>Calvin</hi> judged that the Title <hi>Chriſtianiſſimus</hi> did in no ſenſe belong
to the <hi>French</hi> King, I know not who can excuſe him in giving it unto him.
And if the Subjects of this Nation did generally give the Title, <hi>Defender of the
Faith</hi> unto <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, knowing no ſufficient ground why it ſhould, or
could with truth be given unto him, neither can they be defended or juſtified
in giving it. But why doth M. <hi>Love</hi> inſert or inſiſt upon theſe words, <hi>In caſe
of Life?</hi> Doth he ſuppoſe that the <hi>caſe</hi> he ſpeaks of will alter the caſe of own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the preſent Government, from ſin to righteouſneſs? Or is it his <hi>Principle,</hi>
That to ſave his Life he may do any thing whatſoever, and yet be blameleſs?
But how doth he here toyl and turmoyl himſelf to ſalve the honor of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
onely that he might reproach and calumniate the Parliament with the
more authority &amp; reputation, yet he that ſpent ſo much of his breath (which at
ſuch a time when he had ſo very little of it left, ſhould have bin precious to him)
about vindicating his innocency in owning the preſent Government, though it
was (it ſeems) as much againſt his Principles to own it then when he did own
it, as it is now when he diſowns it (no change, as himſelf profeſſeth, being made
in his Principles by the Scaffold) hath not a word, either here or elſewhere,
to ſpeak for himſelf, hath not a drop of water to waſh off that foul ſtain and
blot from his Conſcience, which it contracted by caſting dirt and mire in the
faces of thoſe, not onely whom he had a few days before owned in the capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of their Government and Authority, but to whom likewiſe he had publique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
given a large teſtimony of Juſtice, Mercy, Wiſdom, Gravity, of being the
Elect of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea and to whom he had publiquely and ſolemnly promiſed
and engaged himſelf, neither to plot, contrive or deſign any thing prejudicial
to them, but to oppoſe any Deſign whatſoever againſt them. Doubtleſs nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>David,</hi> nor <hi>Huſhai,</hi> nor <hi>Calvin,</hi> nor any man either of Conſcience or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,
would have broken or falſified, eſpecially ſo publiquely and in the face of
the Sun, ſuch ſolemn Promiſes and Engagements made to perſons in dignity,
and to whom they had ſo immediately before given ſuch large teſtimony of
many worthy Endowments; and all this without giving the leaſt accompt of
ſuch deſultory and fedifragous practices.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 16.</head>
               <p>It ſeems by the Contents of this Section, that Mr. <hi>Love's Principles</hi> ſtood
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115116:29"/>
fair for the Invaſion of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation by the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Army, but fell
foul upon the <hi>Invaſion of the Scotiſh Nation by the Engliſh Army.</hi> This
he declares againſt: unto the other he is ſilent, as conſenting to it. All the
world may hereby ſee, that his Principles were calculated according to the
exigency of his Intereſt and Faction, and not for the ſervice of Righteouſneſs
and Truth. For was not the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Nation joyned in the ſame Covenant
with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> wherein the <hi>Engliſh</hi> was joyned with the <hi>Scotiſh?</hi> If not,
the <hi>Engliſh</hi> made a very ſorry Bargain in covenanting with the <hi>Scotiſh.</hi> If
ſo, then ſuppoſe the Grounds and Reaſons for the one <hi>Invaſion</hi> and the other,
had been but equal or the ſame, and that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> could give no better an
Accompt otherwiſe of their invading (as Mr. <hi>Love</hi> is pleaſed to clothe a
ſmooth Action with a rough garment) the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Nation, then the <hi>Scotiſh</hi>
are able to give of their invading <hi>England;</hi> yet the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Invaſion of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
is much more juſtifiable or excuſable, then the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> in as
much as the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> were firſt in the Provocation. But (as hath been lately
proved) the ſending of an Army by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> into <hi>Scotland,</hi> is every ways
juſtifiable, warranted by the judgements and deciſions of the beſt learned in
the Civil Laws, who are very competent Judges in the Cauſe, being alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
unrelated unto the perſons or Nations; Whereas there hath not yet
been (nor indeed can there be) any tolerable Accompt given of the <hi>Scotiſh</hi>
Invaſion of this Nation: Beſides what hath been formerly ſaid, to take
off whatſoever may ſeem unjuſt or hard, in the ſending of an Army into <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
by the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> two things further may here be added:
Firſt, that preſently after the Execution of the late King, they (the <hi>Scotiſh</hi>
Nation) proclaimed their own King, King of <hi>England.</hi> Secondly, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
with this Uſurpation over this Nation, they engaged themſelves further
to aſſiſt him in his Acquirement of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Throne. So that when the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Army went into <hi>Scotland,</hi> there was no ſuch thing in being as that <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi>
between the two Nations, which Mr. <hi>Love</hi> ſpeaks of; the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
before this broken it in pieces, and troden it under their feet, and ſo had
abſolutely diſobliged the <hi>Engliſh</hi> from the bands or terms of it. But when
he ſaith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat <hi>becauſe</hi> Scotland <hi>will not be a Commonwealth, they ſhall not be a
People,</hi> doubtleſs in ſtead of ſpeaking his Conſcience, he ſpits out his Gall;
For he could not but know that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had no quarrel at all, took no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
againſt the <hi>Scotiſh,</hi> for chuſing themſelves to be a Kingdom rather then
a Commonwealth; but becauſe they would not ſuffer the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to be a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,
but would compel them by force of arms to be a Kingdom like
to them, yea and to take a King of their chuſing.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Friendly Aſſiſtance</hi> Mr. <hi>Love</hi> ſpeaks of, as given by the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> to
the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> it was rather <hi>Aſsiſtance</hi> then <hi>friendly;</hi> For with that <hi>Aſsiſtance</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:115116:29"/>
they gave they mingled much Hoſtility, behaving themſelves like perſons
light-fingered, who when a well furniſhed houſe is on fire, are eaſily invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to <hi>aſsiſt</hi> in the quenching of it, and very poſſibly may do ſome ſervice this
way: but their eye is more upon booty, then ſervice or aſſiſtance. However,
if the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> have given <hi>aſsiſtance</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> worthy Mr. <hi>Love</hi>'s Epithite,
the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are not behinde-hand with them in that kinde of courteſie. A
<hi>friendly Aſsiſtance</hi> was very lately given to the Covenanting Party in <hi>Scotland,</hi>
when they ſtood in mickle need of it by the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and this not onely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
any covenanted hire, but alſo without any uncovenanted ſpoyl or plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.
The <hi>Scotiſh</hi> were double paid for their <hi>Aſsiſtance,</hi> by the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> were royal, and gave theirs freely. I ſhall not diſturb Mr. <hi>Love</hi> in his
<hi>cleaving to his Oaths, Vows, Covenants, and Proteſtations;</hi> Nor do I marvel
at all, that he ſhould <hi>rather deſire to dye a Covenant-keeper, then live a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-breaker:</hi>
but this I confeſs I do more then marvel at; That this being
his deſire, he ſhould be no more loyal and true to it, then both to live and die,
not a <hi>Covenant-keeper</hi> but a <hi>Covenant-breaker,</hi> and this in the main and moſt
important Articles of the Covenant, ſuch I mean, which reſpect the Safety,
Peace and Liberties of the Nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 17.</head>
               <p>His good wiſhes to the City of <hi>London,</hi> God perform; his fears may
they vaniſh, as the grounds of them here expreſſed are (for the moſt part)
empty and light. As to <hi>contempt of the Miniſtery;</hi> the number (I confeſs)
of the children of this guilt, is too great, the Lord in mercy leſſen it. Yet
(bleſſed be God) it is not ſo great as the Arithmetique of Mr. <hi>Love</hi>'s known
principles computeth it. They are not all guilty of <hi>contempt of the Miniſtery,</hi>
who do not honor every man that calleth himſelf a Miniſter, or that preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
with the inviſible Character of Impoſition of hands upon him; The <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi>
of ſome, who look to be honored as <hi>Miniſters,</hi> may rather be matter
of wiſdom and duty then of ſin. There are ſundry kindes of Miniſters, from
whom men are commanded by God to <hi>turn away.</hi> Such as are <hi>Clouds without
water,</hi> and full of fire in ſtead thereof, ſuch as are <hi>raging waves of the ſea, foam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
out their own ſhame,</hi> ſuch as ordinarily <hi>build hey, and ſtubble, and wood, in
ſtead of ſilver, gold, and precious ſtones:</hi> the Judgements and Conſciences of
underſtanding men will not ſuffer them to honor; But Mr. <hi>Love</hi> here, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the Politique Dialect of his Tribe, would fain have the neglect,
which many Miniſters very deſervedly ſuffer, to be thought, not the neglect
of their perſons, but of their Function and <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> that ſo themſelves may
not be ſuſpected as acceſſary to it; Whereas the certain truth is, that far the
greateſt part of that which he here calls the <hi>Contempt of the Miniſtery,</hi> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115116:30"/>
elſe but a Ruſh growing out of the mire of the Miniſters themſelves.
However, if Mr. <hi>Love</hi> made an eſtimate of the <hi>Contempt of the Miniſtery</hi> in
the City of <hi>London,</hi> either by his own Pariſh and People, or by the view and
bulk of his more uſual Auditory, he had (I preſume) no great reaſon to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie
evil or danger againſt the City for that ſin.</p>
               <p>What he means by <hi>Oppoſition againſt Reformation,</hi> is (I ſuppoſe) too well
known, to be looked upon by men acquainted with the ways, methods and
grounds of Gods Judgements, as any thing much endangering the City in this
kinde. <hi>Oppoſition</hi> (I confeſs) <hi>againſt</hi> that <hi>Reformation</hi> of the hearts, lives and
ways of men, which the Scriptures every where with all importunity preſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the Conſciences of men, is a ſad ſymptom of imminent danger to a City or
People where it is general; But <hi>Oppoſition</hi> to that which in the Dialect of <hi>High
Presbytery</hi> (which Mr. <hi>Love</hi> much uſeth) is termed <hi>Reformation,</hi> is little ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomatical
in that kinde.</p>
               <p>There is the ſame Conſideration of his <hi>Covenant-breaking.</hi> There is a <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-breaking,</hi>
which (doubtleſs) hath <hi>brought London</hi> much <hi>lower,</hi> then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
it ſhould or needed to have been, and which, if not more repented of,
will <hi>lay it</hi> yet much <hi>lower.</hi> But the Execution of Juſtice upon the late King,
the Non-admiſſion of the preſent King of <hi>Scotland</hi> to the Engliſh Throne, the
Non-elevation of the Standard of High Presbytery, the Non-oppoſing of all
that Mr. <hi>Love</hi> oppoſed, under the name and notion of Error and Hereſie, the
Non-forbearance of ſending an Army into <hi>Scotland,</hi> which are ſufficiently
known to be meant by Mr. <hi>Love</hi>'s <hi>Covenant-breaking;</hi> theſe are ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
any ways prognoſtique of evil towards the City, that to men of free and
ſound judgements, they are auſpicious, of a good and gracious preſage.</p>
               <p>What he means by his <hi>General Apoſtacy,</hi> his Principles conſidered, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs
I underſtand not. He denies a poſſibility of <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from any thing that
is truly good or pleaſing unto God: and how Apoſtatizing from that which
is otherwiſe, as from Hypocriſie, Formality, Lukewarmneſs or the like, ſhould
be of any ill abode or preſage unto men, oppoſeth my apprehenſions. True it
is, that the <hi>City</hi> (as he ſaith) is a great <hi>Receptacle of Error,</hi> though, <hi>of All,</hi> I
cannot ſay with him; But firſt, all that Mr. <hi>Love</hi> calleth <hi>Error,</hi> is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<hi>Error,</hi> or proved to be <hi>Error</hi> becauſe he ſo calleth it. Doubtleſs Mr. <hi>Love</hi>
was not greater then <hi>Paul,</hi> and therefore <hi>knew but in part:</hi> Now he that <hi>knows</hi>
but <hi>in part,</hi> is not competent to determine in whole. Secondly, A great part
of thoſe <hi>Errors</hi> with which the City is really polluted, call Mr. <hi>Love</hi> and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
of his Sect, if not <hi>Patres,</hi> yet <hi>Patronos;</hi> If he and others of his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows
did not broach them, yet have they drawn them forth, and given the
City to drink. Thirdly, Another conſiderable part of them, are the legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate
Iſſue of his and their ſpurious Doctrines, and nothing elſe but the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115116:30"/>
natural and expreſs conſequents of thoſe unſound principles, wherewith he
ſeaſoned many. But I truſt that the light of the <hi>Truth as it is</hi> in <hi>Jeſus</hi> breaking
forth dayly with greater brightneſs, will ſcatter (a great part at leaſt of) that
miſt of <hi>errours,</hi> which yet much darkeneth the City (though it be a <hi>Goſhen,</hi>
compared with any other City that I know, or have heard of, throughout
the world) ſo that the errours yet reſident in it, ſhall not be the ruine
of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18, 19, 20" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD upon Section 18, 19, 20.</head>
               <p>In theſe three Sections he commends himſelf in five particulars of ſpiritual
advice unto the inhabitants of the City.</p>
               <p>Firſt, He <hi>beggs</hi> of them <hi>to love their painful and godly Miniſters;</hi> but
leſt there ſhould be <hi>error in perſonâ</hi> he preſently informs them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he means
<hi>Presbyterian.</hi> If theſe were <hi>ſometimes counted the Chariots and horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
of Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>are now the great eye-ſore;</hi> I fear it is becauſe they are
turn'd to be the <hi>Chariots and horſe-men</hi> of <hi>Aram.</hi> But to whom are they
<hi>the great eye-ſore</hi> he ſpeaks of? I ſuppoſe he means, to the State, and men
in power. I confeſs there is ground enough for Maſter <hi>Love</hi> to <hi>ſuſpect</hi> (I
am willing to think that he uſeth the word <hi>know</hi> in the loweſt ſignification)
that the perſons he ſpeaks of are <hi>a great eye-ſore</hi> unto theſe men, and many
others there being ſo much viſible in many of them, which cannot lightly but
offend and grieve the eyes of all beholders, whoſe eyes are not of the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution
and temper with theirs. But the ſpirit of High-Presbytery is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
querulous and effeminate. If the State will not fulfill all their pleaſure and
gratifie them <hi>in toto &amp; in ſolido</hi> of all they demand, or expect, it preſently
caſts them into fits of paſſion and diſcontent; they are men neglected and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed.
Setting aſide what hath been done to a few of the ſons of this late
Conſpiracy againſt the State they have no ground at all from any meaſure they
have received from the State, to judge themſelves any <hi>great eye-ſore</hi> to it.
I know not what they would have more from the State, then what they have;
unleſs it be, <hi>All things under their feet.</hi> When he tells them, that <hi>ten of
their godly Miniſters are taken from them at one blow,</hi> I know not how
he will make up his account, unleſs he reckons himſelf for more then the one
half of them. As for thoſe who <hi>fled from them, when none purſued them,</hi>
but their own guilt, he cannot upon any competent account of truth number
theſe amongſt thoſe, that were <hi>taken from them</hi> by others. But what <hi>blow</hi>
was it, by which ſo many were <hi>taken away</hi> from them, as were <hi>taken?</hi> Or who
gave this <hi>blow?</hi> When God caſt off the ten tribes he imputes it to their Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.
<hi>Thy calf, O Samaria hath caſt thee off<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Hoſ. 8. So when He and the
<hi>Jews</hi> were parted, or <hi>ſeparated</hi> the one from the other, He imputeth
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115116:31"/>
this ſeparation to their ſins, <hi>Your iniquities have ſeparated between you and
your God, Eſa. 59.</hi> That which in puniſhments juſtly inflicted, is afflicting,
or deſtroying, is not to be charged upon the Judge, but upon the offence
and crime committed. Upon this account the <hi>blow,</hi> by which Mr. <hi>Love</hi>
tells the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> that ſo many of their <hi>godly Miniſters (ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo
ſit venia) were taken from them,</hi> was not given either by the Parliament,
Councell of State, or High Court of Juſtice, but by their own ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
and treaſonable practiſes againſt the State and Common-wealth:
theſe are they which have taken away ſo many of their Miniſters at once.
Theſe Miniſters were no waies neceſſitated to practiſe that evill, which
they did; but their Judges were neceſſitated in point of Conſcience, and
by the command of God, to inflict that puniſhment upon them which they
now ſuffer for their evill; therefore this puniſhment is not to be imputed
to their Judges, but to themſelves, and their own miſcarriages.</p>
               <p>2. <hi>He exhorts the ſaid perſons of his preſent addreſſe, (the Inhabitants
of the City)</hi> That they would ſubmit themſelves to Church-Government,
which would lay a curb and reſtraint upon their luſts, <hi>telling them,</hi> that it is a
golden and eaſie yoke, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The exhortation (in generall) is weighty and worthy by all men to be
received: <hi>Church-Government,</hi> as the kind, and conſtitution, together with
the adminiſtration of it, may, and ought to be, is of a moſt Soveraign ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
and import for that great end he ſpeaks of: But that <hi>Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
which Mr. <hi>Love</hi> intends, at leaſt as far as the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world hath had
the triall of it hitherto, in ſuch adminiſtrations of it, as it hath found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
men, hath given but a very ſlender teſtimony of any ſuch heavenly
vertue or vigor in it. <hi>Hâc non ſucc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſit: aliâ aggrediundum eſt viâ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. He admoniſheth them to take heed <hi>of Doctrines that come under the
n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion of new lights:</hi> If by <hi>new lights,</hi> he means Doctrines brought into the
world ſince the compleating of the Scriptures, and which cannot by a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimate
and clear deſcent derive their pedigree from theſe, the admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
is wholeſome and grave; but if by his <hi>new lights,</hi> he means all ſuch
Doctrines or Tenets, which have not received countenance or approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
from the generality of Miniſters of a later Edition, and ſince the
times of <hi>Luthers</hi> and <hi>Calvins</hi> Reformations, his advice is indeed arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially
calculated for the Meridian of high Presbytery, but very diſſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
to the advancement and growth of Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>4. He exhorteth them to <hi>bewaile their great loſſe in the taking away of
ſo many Miniſters out of their City;</hi> and then recounting the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
of them, finds them, <hi>if he mistakes not, ten;</hi> under the covert of
ſuch an exception or reſerve, he might as truly have ſaid, they had
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115116:31"/>
been twenty. He ſpeaks of ſome, as being in <hi>baniſhment.</hi> Thoſe of them in
this condition, were adjudged thither by no other Judges then their own
Conſciences. When the City of refuge is ſought unto, it is a ſign that there
is bloud ſhed, and that there is ſome avenger of bloud that follows the
chaſe. The Miniſters he ſpeaks of, he doth the rather lift up unto heaven,
with thoſe glorious Elogiums he beſtows on them, that ſo he may
caſt thoſe ſo much the deeper into hell in the peoples thoughts, whom he
would have lookt upon as the Authors of their <hi>taking away.</hi> But the Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factour,
as hath been ſaid, not the Judge, is the Author of his ſufferings:
If they were <hi>lights,</hi> they were far more <hi>burning</hi> then <hi>ſhining,</hi> but with an
un-hallowed fire: if <hi>Starres,</hi> ſtarres they were of a very Malignant influence
upon the State where they liv'd, and in their Conjunction, made a very
dangerous and fiery conſtellation: Thoſe of whom (as the Scripture teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth)
<hi>the world was not worthy,</hi> were a generation of men of another ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
holy, humble, and harmleſſe, were content to ſuffer from the world, to
do the world ſervice. Mr. <hi>Love's</hi> men are a generation that muſt have the
world bow down unto them, and lick the duſt at their feet, to ſtrengthen
their hand to do them ſervice: neglect from men, is as the ſhadow of death
unto them.</p>
               <p>5. <hi>(And laſtly) He gives them a brief Item,</hi> to take heed of being forward
to ingage in a war againſt their godly Brethren in Scotland. <hi>If theſe</hi> godly
Brethren in Scotland <hi>had not been</hi> forward to ingage in a war againſt them,
<hi>the Counſell had been</hi> Chriſtian <hi>and prudent. But inaſmuch as theſe</hi> godly
Brethren <hi>firſt</hi> ingaged <hi>in a</hi> war againſt their godly Brethren <hi>here, (as hath
been formerly ſhewed) it is no point of</hi> Chriſtianity <hi>or prudence
to demurre upon a courſe of defence, or of prevention of the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 21.</head>
               <p>There is a red threed of revenge againſt the Parliament and State,
ſtruck quite thorough this fare-well piece of Mr. <hi>Loves</hi> to the world, from
the very beginning to the end of it, viſible enough (and indeed, too much)
in every Section, which creates a ſad jealouſie with me, left his <hi>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectonicus,</hi>
his predominant end in his laſt addreſſe on earth, was to have
the men in preſent Power under the hardeſt and moſt hatefull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ment
with the people, that he could imagine or deviſe. In many paſſages he
hales in by head and ſhoulders ſuch things, which a man cannot tell how or
why they ſhould come there, but only to aſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſe the State, and to enve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom
the ſpirits of the people againſt them. In theſe his Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
to the <hi>godly Miniſtery</hi> (as he terms it) <hi>of the City,</hi> he doth his beſt to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115116:32"/>
make them believe (for he affirms that he knoweth it) that <hi>they are maligned
and threatned;</hi> and this the people muſt conceive to be by the State: yea, and
the cauſe and ground hereof muſt be ſuppoſed to be for <hi>ſetting themſelves
againſt the ſins and Apoſtacies of the times,</hi> for <hi>his faithfulneſs wherein
he himſelf had procured ill will from men.</hi> Poor man! Doth he call <hi>his
ſin againſt God his high crimes and offences againſt the Parliament in his
late and great miſcarriages,</hi> for which himſelf confeſſeth (in his laſt Petition to
the Parliament, as was formerly ſhewed) that <hi>the Sentence of death was
juſtly paſſed on him by the High-Court of Juſtice;</hi> doth he (I ſay) call
<hi>ſin againſt God, high crimes great miſcarriages his faithfulneſs in ſetting
himſelf againſt the ſins and Apoſtacies of this preſent age?</hi> I confeſs if
theſe were his <hi>faithfulneſs</hi> in that kind he ſpeaks of, it was his <hi>faithfulneſs
that procured him the ill-will of men.</hi> If ſuch notions and conceits as theſe
were the foundation of that <hi>abundant peace of his Conſcience,</hi> and which he
ſaith he <hi>hath with God,</hi> and with which he <hi>dieth,</hi> I fear he may be too truly
compared to the fooliſh builder, who neglected the <hi>rock,</hi> and <hi>built his houſe
upon the ſand;</hi> which ſoon after <hi>fell,</hi> and <hi>great was the fall thereof.</hi> But
to perſwade the <hi>godly Miniſters</hi> of his preſent addreſs, (together with the
people) the more effectually that they were certainly <hi>maligned</hi> and <hi>threatned,</hi>
he will needs (upon this account) lift up a prayer for them, in the words of
thoſe Chriſtians, <hi>Act. 4. 29. And now Lord behold their threatnings, and
grant that thy ſervants may preach the word with all boldneſs.</hi> But is not
this an horrid prophanation of the ſacred Ordinance of Prayer, and of him
that hath appointed it; to repreſent perſons unto God as guilty of ſuch crimes
whereof he knows them to be innocent; eſpecially when he alſo that prayeth,
hath no tolerable ground to judge them ſuch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as they are repreſented by him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
God in his Prayer? What ground or colour of ground, had Maſter <hi>Love</hi>
to accuſe the Parliament or State before God of <hi>threatning the godly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
of the City</hi> for preaching <hi>the Word of God?</hi> What <hi>Miniſter</hi> did they
ever <hi>threaten</hi> upon any ſuch account as this? Poſſibly ſuch <hi>Miniſters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s</hi> who in
their preachings have turn'd the good <hi>Word of God,</hi> and Goſpel of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
into fire-brands of Sedition, into ſcurrilous and bitter invectives againſt thoſe,
whom God hath ſet in Authority over them, who in ſtead of lifting up their
voices like Trumpets, to make the people to know their abominations, have lift
them like Trumpets to provoke and animate them to commit abominations;
poſſibly, (I ſay) ſuch <hi>Miniſters</hi> as theſe they have diſcountenanced in ſuch
ways of impiety and prophanation of the Word of God as theſe.</p>
               <p>His <hi>perſwaſion</hi> that <hi>the Presbyterial Government makes moſt for purity
and for unity throughout the Churches of the Saints,</hi> the experience which
the world hath had of this Government in thoſe places, or Churches, where it
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115116:32"/>
hath had its <hi>throne,</hi> doth not much countenance or confirm: but I ſhall not
here counter-argue it. Whereas he <hi>beggs</hi> of the Miniſters that they would <hi>keep
up Church-Government,</hi> and had onely added, and not intermeddle with the
<hi>Civil-Government</hi> of the State, his advice had been both Chriſtian and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Section 22.</head>
               <p>I will not ſay that Maſter <hi>Love</hi> here <hi>freeth all the Miniſters in the City,</hi>
thoſe onely excepted who are already <hi>diſcovered</hi> from having a hand in his <hi>bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs</hi>
(he diſlikes, it ſeems, the word <hi>Plot)</hi> in ſuch a ſenſe, wherein not long
ſince he <hi>freed</hi> himſelf, from whatſoever was not, or could not (as he thought)
be proved againſt him. I judge it not improbable, but that the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of his
exemption may be <hi>free</hi> from all interpoſure of particularities of advice for the
driving on M. <hi>Loves deſigne</hi> (this word he owns in one of his Petitions though the
word <hi>Plot,</hi> grates upon his ſpirit) yea (poſſibly) they may be <hi>free</hi> in reſpect of
the knowledge of the particularities of the method, and tranſactions, by which
the Deſigne was carryed on and ripened from time to time, by the Arch-Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers:
ſuch works of darkneſs are in danger of coming abroad into the light, before
their time, and ſo to miſchieve or deſtroy the workmen, in caſe the number of
thoſe, who either ſhall meet frequently for the managing and forming of them,
or to whom the particulars of them ſhall be imparted, be too great. It is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
ſeen, but that that which is known to many<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſoon after comes to be known
unto all. Yet I beleeve there is hardly any Miniſter of the Presbyterian per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion
about the City, but knew well enough that there was <hi>Scotch</hi>-Ale in
brewing, and that Maſter <hi>Love</hi> and his Complices were not aſleep as to their
Intereſt and cauſe. Yea, and that from time to time, though they could not
call Maſter <hi>Loves</hi> Deſigne by its proper name, yet they prayed heartily in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
and covert terms for the proſperity of it. But Maſter <hi>Loves Conſcience</hi>
now upon the Scaffold, tells him (it ſeems) a quite contrary t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le, to what it
told him a few days before. When he was a Petitioner to the Parliament for
his life, his <hi>Conſcience</hi> told him that he had <hi>Sinned againſt God,</hi> that his
<hi>late miſcarriages were great,</hi> his <hi>crimes and offences againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
high,</hi> &amp;c. But in the interim (it ſeems) the <hi>Rabbies</hi> of his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> had been with him, and ſhin'd a <hi>new light</hi>
into him. About the entertainment whereof, had he followed his own
Counſel directed unto others in the like caſe, (formerly mentioned) and
had <hi>taken heed</hi> of receiving it, it had been much better and ſafer for
him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:115116:33"/>
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 23.</head>
               <p>What M. <hi>Love</hi> gives in honor to his <hi>Congregation,</hi> I ſhall not take from
them: Onely what he gives unto himſelf in this kind, as, 1. That <hi>he ſhould
never have parted from them had not death parted them: 2. That he ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
unto death with all Christian meekneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. I make ſome queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
he had right to give it, or no. For, he that had parted from one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation
upon a far different occaſion from that of death he ſpeaks of;
why might he not, his judgment remaining the ſame touching a lawfulneſſe
of parting, have parted from another, and another after that, upon a like
occaſion? Men may be confident of their preſent intentions and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes:
but to propheſie of their future, is to run an adventure. But whereas
he profeſſeth <hi>his ſubmiſſion unto death with all Chriſtian meekneſſe,</hi> I leave
him to be judged out of his own mouth, in this very diſcourſe, wherewith
he hath avenged himſelf on his Judges, whom he calls his adverſaries, to
the uttermoſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 24.</head>
               <p>In the beginning of this Section he profeſſeth his <hi>deſire to juſtifie God,
and to condemne himſelf.</hi> A <hi>Christian</hi> and worthy profeſſion! But that
which he profeſſeth a deſire to do, he doth very faintly, and by halfs: But
that which is contrary to what he deſires, as he ſaith, to do, he doth vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly,
and with his might. In his <hi>juſtifying of God,</hi> he is very generall, and
faint: and yet more generall and ſuperficiall, in <hi>condemning himſelf.</hi> But
in the juſtifying of himſelf, and condemning others, he is inlarg'd beyond
his line. For the <hi>juſtifying of God,</hi> he ſaith only, that <hi>he is righteous:</hi> in the
<hi>condemning of himſelf,</hi> he ſaith no more, but onely, <hi>I have ſinned,</hi> (which
the moſt innocent and righteous perſon under heaven may ſay truly.) But
for the <hi>juſtifying,</hi> and commending of himſelf, with a mixture of inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
againſt others, how copious and eloquent is he? Firſt he ſaith, <hi>his
bloud ſhall not be ſpilt for nought;</hi> wherein he make's himſelf equall with
the Saints he mentioneth from the <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 2. That he <hi>may do more good by
his death, then by his life:</hi> which, though it may be true enough in a ſence
little to his honor, yet in his notion muſt imply, either that his Oration,
which he was now uttering, was ſo effectuall and full of power, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of thoſe that heard it, would either be converted, or els much edified by
it; or els that his dying with ſo much courage in ſuch a worthy cauſe, as he
was now to ſuffer for, would make others confident in the further mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
and proſecution of it, whereby God ſhould be much glorified. 3. He
ſings over his former note of confidence, <hi>I bleſſe my God, I have not the leaſt
trouble,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I die with as much quietneſſe of mind,</hi> &amp;c. By which he doth not
only commend himſelf as one of the firſt-born ſons of Faith, but far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:115116:33"/>
inſinuates the goodneſſe and juſtifiableneſſe of his cauſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
the people may be the more incens'd againſt his Judges. 4. He ſaith,
that he ſees that <hi>men hunger after his fleſh, and thirſt after his blood,</hi> which
<hi>hastens his happineſſe, and their ruine,</hi> &amp;c. wherein at once he <hi>juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi>
himſelf in the higheſt, and condemneth others proportionably.
5. He ſaith, his <hi>blood is innocent blood;</hi> (is this to condemne himſelf,
and not plainly to condemne others by his ſelf-juſtification?) 6. He
ſaith, that <hi>his dead body will be a morſell, which he believes will hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
be digeſted, and that his blood will be bad food,</hi> &amp;c. What are theſe
but <hi>Rhetoricall</hi> flouriſhes of his own righteouſneſſe and innocency, full
of reflexion upon his Judges, as men that had ſinned with an high hand
againſt the peace and ſafety of the Common-wealth, by ſentencing him
to die.</p>
               <p>7. (And laſtly) that he may proclaim his innocency, as well in the Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,
as Affirmative, he ſaith, <hi>Mine is not Malignant bloud, though, &amp;c.</hi> was
Mr. <hi>Loves deſire to condemn himſelf,</hi> in ſpeaking theſe things; or are they the
words of a man taking ſhame unto himſelf, and <hi>juſtifying God</hi> thereby:
The truth is, he hath <hi>condemn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi> himſelf by ſpeaking them, all along calling
<hi>evill good, and good evill, putting darkneſſe for light, and light for darkneſſe,
bitter for ſweet, and ſweet for bitter,</hi> ſtumblings and miſtakes of a very
ſad import, ſo neer the threſhold of death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 25.</head>
               <p>In the beginning of this Section, he ſeems (in part) to repent of the
former, but his words are of no good conſiſtence. He proves God to be
<hi>very just,</hi> by this, that his priſon <hi>was not his Hell,</hi> &amp;c. inaſmuch as <hi>he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
it.</hi> This is an argument to prove him gracious, or mercifull; but that
men have not in puniſhment, what they have deſerved in ſin, hath no face
of a proof that God is <hi>very juſt.</hi> If Mr. <hi>Love</hi> had here alſo ſtood upon his
Juſtification, and ſaid, <hi>I have not deſerved it,</hi> his Argument had been more
congruous, though the Sentence more culpable: yet in the ſequel of this
Section alſo, he reſumes his ſweet morſells of ſelf-juſtification, and ſelf-commendation,
and puts them again under his tongue. Here he aſſumeth the
honour of <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tyrdome</hi> unto himſelf, <hi>Whatſoever men judge of me,</hi> I <hi>am a
Martyr too.</hi> I have read that <hi>Petilian,</hi> againſt whom S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> wrote, cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized
<hi>Iudas</hi> for a <hi>Martyr</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Donne.</hi> Pſeudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. ca. 2.</note>: and that the <hi>Circumcelliones,</hi> whom the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
likewiſe mentioneth, were very earneſt with thoſe they met, to kil them,
that ſo they might be accounted <hi>Martyrs</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>teol. Hae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. l. 3. c. 19.</note>. And therefore to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
of Mr. <hi>Love, What ſhould a dying man be proud of?</hi> anſwer may be,
that a dying man, eſpecially touch'd with a ſpirit of vain-glory, may very
poſſibly <hi>be proud</hi> that he ſhall die a <hi>Martyr,</hi> and enjoy the honour of ſuch a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:115116:34"/>
death afterwards. Neither is there any great weight in theſe glorious expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <hi>Welcome Scaffold, welcome Axe, welcome Death, welcome Block,
welcome all, becauſe it will ſend me to my Fathers houſe,</hi> conſidering that
one of the worſt of the Heathen Emperours died with theſe words in his mouth,
<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t puto, Deus fio, i.e.</hi> Me thinks I am even now ready to be made a God.
We gave (upon the firſt Section, as I remember) a more particular account
by what winde Maſter <hi>Love</hi> might very probably ſayl into that Port of Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
wherein we here finde him; and yet make Shipwrack too in the Harbour,
in caſe he were not the more circumſpect. But Maſter <hi>Love</hi> muſt the rather
be a <hi>Martyr,</hi> that ſo his Judges may be perſecutors. Their defamation to the
people, is an Oar that he plyes hard upon all occaſions. Witneſs the words a
little preceding thoſe laſt recited: <hi>Would I have renounced my Covenant, and
debauched my Conſcience, and ventured my ſoul, there might have been
more hopes of ſaving my life,</hi> &amp;c. Unworthy man! who required of him,
either the <hi>renouncing of his Covenant,</hi> or <hi>the debauching of his Conſcience,</hi>
&amp;c. in order to the <hi>ſaving of his life?</hi> Or if he calls either the diſowning
of his late treaſonable negotiations with the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> King, Kirk, and Nation or
the owning of the preſent Government, either a <hi>renouncing of his Covenant,</hi>
or a <hi>debauching of his Conſcience,</hi> or the <hi>venturing of his Soul,</hi> he vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily
and freely of himſelf did all theſe (as hath been ſhewed over and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
from his own Narrative and Petitions) <hi>for the ſaving of his life.</hi> And
what he ſhould further mean by <hi>the renouncing of his Covenant, debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
&amp;c. I confeſs I underſtand not, unleſs it ſhould be the taking of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement
impoſed by the State. But that he voluntarily and of his own accord
engaged himſelf (in his laſt Petition to the Houſe) to do all things required, that
are lightly imaginable to be required, in that Engagement, was likewiſe formerly
proved from his own cleer and expreſs words. Nor is the taking of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement
in that formality of words wherein it is recommended by the State
unto the Nation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> any ways inconſiſtent with the <hi>Covenant,</hi> no not in any lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
or Grammatical ſenſe that can be put upon it: nor needs any man either <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch
his Conſcience,</hi> or <hi>venture his ſoul</hi> in the taking of it. I fear there
are more <hi>Conſciences debauched,</hi> and ſouls ventured, by the refuſal, then by
the taking of it. By the way, if Maſter <hi>Love</hi> had <hi>ventured his ſoul,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
by taking the Engagement, owning the preſent Government, or the like, it
is a demonſtrative Argument<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> according to his principles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he neither was a
Saint nor one of the Elect of God, becauſe the ſouls of all ſuch are out of
all poſſibility of miſcarrying.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:115116:34"/>
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 26.</head>
               <p>In this Section we have little obſervable, but onely further inculcations of his
courage and confidence in the face and preſence of Death (as if he were jealous
the people would not believe him at this point, without much importunity of
Aſſertion) together with ſome more gentle inſinuations then formerly of his
Innocency; onely the laſt clauſe here is very remarkable, <hi>God will judge all men,
I will judge none:</hi> When he ſaith that <hi>He will judge none,</hi> doth he not retract
and cancel all the hard ſayings formerly uttered by him, wherein he had judged
and condemned his Judges and the State? But welcome Repentance, though at
the Eleventh hour of the day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27, 28" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 27, 28.</head>
               <p>The heart and ſtrength of theſe Sections alſo, is of the ſame Argument with
the former; he diſplays the Banner of his Confidence yet again and again before
the people: Thoſe Expreſſions, <hi>Though men kill me, they cannot damn me;
though they thruſt me out of the world,</hi> &amp;c. are of a Suſpitious interpretation,
That Mr. <hi>Love</hi> was not yet perfectly recovered out of his fit of Paſſion: The
denial of Power, in ſuch caſes, as that wherein he now ſpeaks, uſually ſuppoſeth
a will or diſpoſition to do that, for the doing whereof, power is wanting. Nor
doth he ſay much either for his own comfort, or for the edification of the
people, in ſaying, That the men who <hi>kill him</hi> (I ſuppoſe he means, who by the
Sword of Juſtice take his life from him, which is very unproperly termed
killing) <hi>cannot damn him.</hi> For firſt, queſtionleſs all the people very well knew,
<hi>That men could not damn him:</hi> Therefore the ſaying turned to no account of
Edification unto them: Nor ſecondly, was it much for his own comfort, that
the men he ſpeaks of <hi>could not damn him;</hi> becauſe had they had ſuch a power,
he had been in never a whit the more danger from ſuffering from them in that
kinde, there being not the leaſt inclination or will in them to make uſe of ſuch
a power, in caſe they had had it. As they that die in the Faith of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
are in never the more danger of being <hi>damned</hi> by God, becauſe he hath power
to <hi>damn them;</hi> That juſtice, of which the <hi>men</hi> Mr. <hi>Love</hi> ſpeaks of, were Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
appointed by God, required onely his natural life from him: And far was
it from the hearts or thoughts of the Miniſters hereof, to require more: Nay,
had not Juſtice very importunely, and with a loud voice called and cryed unto
them for that life of his, which is now taken from him, far had they been from
taking or deſiring it. So that it was but a very Unchriſtian ſtrain of Mr. <hi>Loves</hi>
exulcerated Spirit againſt them, to ſay or inſinuate, That they <hi>hungred after
his fleſh, and were thirſty for his blood:</hi> And much more to intimate, as if they
had a minde or will to damn him, in caſe they had power. Was it either Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
or proper, for Mr. <hi>Love</hi> to ſanctifie himſelf unto prayer, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
now to pray his laſt, by taking ſuch words unto him as theſe? How impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115116:35"/>
and with what over-weeningneſs of conceit of his own worth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency,
he transfers thoſe words of that Great Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 6, 7. upon
himſelf, I ſhall not ſtand to argue. And with what truth he could ſay in the
Apoſtles ſence (wherein doubtleſs he would be underſtood to ſpeak) <hi>I have
kept the Faith,</hi> I leave to his Great Lord and Maſter, both his and mine to
determine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29, 30" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 29, 30.</head>
               <p>In theſe two Sections Mr. <hi>Love</hi> commends by Prayer, both himſelf and his
own Soul, as all others whom he judged it meet to pray for, unto God. In a
great part of this Prayer, and of the particular Requeſts made therein, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend
nothing but what is ſavory and Chriſtian. I truſt that theſe words
towards the latter end of this prayer, <hi>Lord hear, pardon all his infirmities,
wipe away his iniquities by the blood of Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> carried in them an impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite
Repentance, both of that <hi>ſin againſt God, of thoſe high Crimes, and late
great miſcarriages againſt the Parliament;</hi> for which (as himſelf a few days
before this Prayer, confeſſed) he was juſtly condemned, as likewiſe of all thoſe
moſt untrue, bitter and Unchriſtian invectives uttered againſt the Parliament
and State in this Speech upon the Scaffold, together with all the reſt of the ſins
of his life. And when in his laſt Petition, he prayeth to <hi>be received by God,
pure, and ſpotleſs, and blameleſs before him in love:</hi> I truſt he prayed not <hi>to be
received</hi> by God as any other perſon, then what he really and in truth was;
and conſequently, That he was <hi>blameleſs in love.</hi> If ſo, then was that ſpirit of
ſpleen and Unchriſtian bitterneſs, by which he ſpake ſo many unſeemly things
againſt thoſe, who little deſerved it at his hand, in the foregoing Speech, by this
time vaniſhed and gone out of him; And indeed it was now high time to caſt
him out, becauſe there had been no entrance for Mr. <hi>Love</hi> into his Fathers
houſe (he ſpeaks of) in his company: When he ſaith, That <hi>he had made God
his Hope and his Confidence from his youth up,</hi> I wiſh that his heart did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
him; It is not lightly poſſible that men ſhould labor ſo in the fire, as Mr.
<hi>Love</hi> did, to promote or uphold a carnal and worldly Intereſt, who truly
make God their <hi>Hope and Confidence.</hi> As in his zeal for God, and for the
<hi>bringing of the ſouls of men to heaven,</hi> he was equalized, if not exceeded by
the Jews in <hi>Pauls</hi> days, and by the Scribes and Phariſees in our Saviours, (who
<hi>compaſſed Sea and Land to make one Proſelyte)</hi> ſo was he alſo in his glorying or
boaſting in God. Foundations, not Buildings or Superſtructions, are the
great Oracles in Religion to be conſulted about the Spiritual Eſtates of men.
After he had gloried this great glorying in God, <hi>Lord, thou haſt ſetled this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion
in my heart, That as ſoon as ever the blow is given to divide my head from
my body, I ſhall be united to my Head in Heaven,</hi> he prayeth thus, <hi>O bleſſed
Jeſus, apply thy blood, not onely for my juſtification unto life, but alſo for my
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:115116:35"/>
comfort, for the quieting of my ſoul,</hi> &amp;c. And again, <hi>Hear the Prayers of all thy
people that have been made for thy ſervant; and though thou haſt denied Prayer,
as to the particular Requeſt concerning my Life; yet let herein the fruit of Prayer
be ſeen, That thou wilt bear up my heart againſt the fear of death.</hi> If the former
glorying had ſucceeded theſe Petitions, and not gone before them, the conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
between the one and the other, had been of a better and more eaſie In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation.
When he prayeth for his <hi>Covenant-keeping-Brethren in the
Kingdom of</hi> Scotland, he prayeth for a Generation of men that is not, <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-keepers</hi>
being ſeveral yeers ſince periſhed from amongſt the Inhabiters of
that Nation: <hi>Covenant-takers</hi> are here generally metempſychoſed into <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-breakers.</hi>
His Petition, <hi>To make England and Scotland one ſtaff in the
Lords hand;</hi> The Lord, I truſt, will ſhortly perform. That he ſhould pray ſo
particularly for men of a Forraign Nation, and for a Brother of remote Blood
(though of near relation in guilt) and not once mention in his Prayer, his near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
relations in Nature, Wife or Children, eſpecially having brought them into
an afflicted and ſad condition by his Miſcarriages, was the obſervation of ſome
ſober men preſent, not without offence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
               <head>ANIMAD. upon Sect. 31.</head>
               <p>I have nothing to Animadvert upon this Section, but onely that which
helps me to hope the better of his preſent Condition; as <hi>viz.</hi> That I perceive no
breathing at all herein of that evil ſpirit of Wrath and Diſcontent, which had
wrought ſo effectually in him until his Prayer (in the two laſt Sections) and the
more immediate approaches of Death. The departure of this ſpirit from him,
before his own, is a ground of good hope, That this latter ſhall not be ſent
thither, from whence the former came.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
